Good morning. Thank you for coming to this room.
The first chat we will have is from Alejandro Cortez.
You will present yourself in a machine.
Let's give him a big applause.
The question is at the end of the session.
Good morning. Do you hear me well?
I will do it without a microphone because I think I can.
I am Alejandro Cortez, a humble teacher.
I have been involved in many things.
I have been involved in engineering, industrial, it is strange.
My fundamental specialty is that I am a forensic and judicial informatic peritoneum.
I have been a lawyer since 1986.
I am a lawyer since 1986.
I was probably not born when I was already in contact with the Bites.
I am an expert in cybersecurity.
I try to make students know something.
I can't do it, but we will continue.
I am a professor of FPL at the School of Engineering and Engineering.
I try to convey everything as possible.
I am a master of international cybersecurity in Ecuador and here in Spain.
I am very passionate about this.
I am a security engineer and an analysis of forensics.
If I am defined, these are the three specialties.
I mix them all.
I am a forensic informatic, a protection of cybercrime,
any fraud or any fraud, I get involved.
It is a problem I have.
I am also a multimedia engineer at ESIC
and I teach at the International School of Pogrado
about the dark web that I use with Python.
I love to use things.
You will see the reason for this chat now.
Public articles, conferences, investigations,
what happens to me in my head,
if I sleep more than six hours, I start to go around and around,
I create an article, a video, or whatever.
My social media channels are on Twitter and Telegram,
and my email is at cortearrobaexerencia.com
in case it is longer than a tweet.
I have open messages,
so you can always write to me and I will see it.
That is something I usually don't see.
I recently discovered that I speak Chinese.
I think I am not going to speak Chinese here,
but a master told me, they speak Chinese.
That destroyed me.
I said, please, send me the WhatsApp,
because I have to say this.
If I speak Chinese, you ask me, what is this?
Let's go to the mess, to the jail or father.
As a forensic engineer,
because if you combine my experience,
the subject of the computer field,
and the engineering, there you have it.
When we do a forensic experience,
we always have to geolocate
how we do the station and where we do it.
We have a protocol for that.
When I go to a station, in a notary,
I say, I go to this place,
but sometimes they call me and tell me,
no, you don't have to go to the site.
Why? Because the tests are there,
I have to get evidence from the place.
If you have to go, you will be charged equally.
That's what this talk gives.
I haven't been to Isla Pérez-Hil,
but I usually go to the local,
with their GPS coordinates,
and it's phenomenal.
The problem is that I have to go to the notary,
or the public notary, depending on who calls me,
if it's the judge,
or the client,
and I have to take him there.
The notary doesn't want to move,
but if he wants to move, I have to take him there.
So I had to cut it off a bit,
because from what we were going to talk about,
there are things I had to camouflage,
because it has a certain confidentiality,
but it is almost 95% true.
Well, they asked me to do a police station,
a police station in my hometown,
I'm from Málaga,
and the plan is that I go from Málaga,
I have continued to keep it,
and I have been allying with the poor people,
they have given me nothing,
and I have come here to ally with them.
Well, I have accepted the budget,
and the fund provision,
and I have to accept it,
I have to do it,
I have to get the digital evidence,
in the site, I say,
well, I have to go, I'm getting lazy,
since the pandemic, I'm getting lazy to move,
but well, I'm going.
So I'm going with the client,
I'm going with the notary,
I'm going to do the extraction.
I like to prepare the things before time,
I'm not going to see what I find.
I like it.
I'm going to a site,
we'll see where it is,
I'm going to check it,
I'll see what I find in the car,
because the same is true,
if the evidence is entered in a armored suit,
and I have to break it,
I have to break it,
I have to carry the biggest one,
well, I'll look where I was at the place,
The GPS says, well, more or less, phenomenal.
The location is fictitious, because I already tell you that I had to change it.
This is a place that I had an office in Malga, more or less, to make the idea.
And now it turns out that I arrive at day D, hour H, notary, present, client, present,
location, fictitious, this coordinate, and the location changes the coordinate.
When I go, the GPS that I carried was not the coordinates that I had located.
I bought it once, twice, changed from GPS, took another, and they are not the coordinates.
The notary, who knows me, already looks at me, he says, oops, something happens to him,
because it is normal, things do not match.
I say, well, where am I?
Actually, they do not match, and, let's see, I like to carry things in the middle.
Well, man, you have many times to improvise, but here, in front of the notary, you cannot improvise.
You have to give security, because if not, the uncle asks you in any story,
he asks you your age and you make mistakes.
In total, my face, worried, no.
The following, as I think I was more worried than when my children were born.
I said, what's going to happen? Well, cancel it.
The notary charges for displacement, charges for everything, and pays for the client,
but in this case, when I cancel it, I say, I have to pay the notary another day.
What's wrong here?
Well, this is little for what I started thinking about.
I do not know, this has never happened to me.
I talk to my fellow experts, I talk to everyone and nobody tells me anything.
This, something strange happens here. I investigate and say, let's see, I'm going to start looking at GPS,
let's see what happens and I find GPS inhibitors.
We have mobile inhibitors when we are near a police station, it is normal,
you are talking on the phone and you hang up.
My mother knows all the nights that I go through the National Police of my neighborhood and they cut me.
But hey, but GPS is more strange, no?
There are GPS inhibitors and they are bought for 4 euros, but this is not a blocker.
The GPS has changed me.
And it scares you, no?
So, look, this is Aliexpress, I have picked it up from there,
you can even connect it directly to the center of the car and say, but no, I don't want to block this.
Something else happens here, no?
They have displaced the signal.
And this, how? This is the place that the GPS sends me and this is the place where I am,
I have to do the peri-sial.
There is a distance of 12 kilometers.
For me it is a 12-kilometer distance, it is a barbarity.
And I say, what's going on?
I investigate, I see the issue of wall-driven,
what happens is that there is a possibility of deceiving the signal of the optometres,
especially in the United States.
You know that truck drivers should not drive for more than two hours,
immediately, three hours, and that goes all in a machine and others,
because they deceive them.
Here not so much, but they deceive them here, they don't care, but in the United States they do.
And it says that the GPS is vulnerable to this issue, no?
And I say, well, but that's the United States, this is bad, no?
I don't know, it's true that Google has already arrived, but when I said this,
Google was not there, no?
I say, well, nothing, let's see.
I keep looking and I find that it can be done a supply of GPS.
And this article, look, it was achieved a kilometer and a half ago in 2008,
more than five years had passed, that is, someone has the technology to move,
that is very dangerous and above all, it can be a risk of security of all levels,
especially if you have a airport nearby or anything nearby,
because imagine a person who is driving a plane and says,
oh, what is not here, although you see the runway, I see the runway,
but it is not 12 kilometers further and instead of landing on the airport,
you get into a polygon.
That is national security is quite important and quite.
And it touches me and I say, go for it, I've already touched the rare case,
it is that someone has to make the easy cases, because I don't get it.
Well, I'll tell you a little bit, in case you don't know how GPS is,
a system that everyone calls it in a way, they invented it in the United States,
there is 31 operating satellites there and the Soviet Union has its system,
in Europe we have ours, in China they have theirs,
and well, there is a great technology behind it,
so that the location is the most precise.
Look, now I will show you the GPS that I have used,
it returns me to the series port, because everything in plane text mode,
and you can always, the most important thing about what returns you is the time,
the GPS coordinates, this is my home from here in Granada,
you don't record it much, because if not, the altitude,
and you say more or less yes, the altitude, and the time, sorry, and the day,
that is the most important thing, the UTC time coordinates GPS,
the altitude at sea level and the date of the satellite.
Well, okay, but it is a georegulation without G,
it is clear, without GPS, right?
So, well, what other ways do we have to locate ourselves?
Well, we can call Legolas, who is a machine and he knows where the sun is,
he knows where it is, okay?
Tranco, also, Tranco, this, how was it, Aragorn,
I call him Tranco, okay?
This man also knows where he is, but I don't have him,
so the people's pastor called him and he knows when the sun comes out,
what time it is, he knows perfectly where it is,
but I don't have anyone close here either, right?
So the object of this conference is, well, working on technology,
how not?
Because we have the Wi-Fi, the Wi-Fi, well, this is such a step,
because this is not important, the important thing is what we are here, right?
We have the 2.4 GHz, which is the most extended, and we have the 5 GHz, right?
Normally, a router is needed and the most important thing about routers
is that, apart from giving access to the internet and others,
well, I love using IP Info.io to locate IP addresses,
and the other things are the derivatives that each one uses, right?
So the most important thing about routers is that most routers
have the BSSID, which is the Chromebook of BASY SERVICE SET INDIVIDEFILE,
it looks like a Mac address, but it's not, it's not,
there are people who mention it, but it's not a Mac, that's precisely, right?
So you can't easily change it because it comes in the ROM of routers,
in the ROM of routers and in the ROM of the Alambri accession points,
that is, if you want to change the direction of the BSSID of a device,
well, nothing, you have to change the ROM, or hack the ROM,
to see who has the technology to take the ROM and reflect it, I don't.
There are people who will be able to, but well, we are already talking about bigger words,
and then solve it again and it works.
Well, with two cables, maybe three, but to reflect a ROM?
No. Well, it is confused with the SSID, which is the name of the Wi-Fi,
but the name of the Wi-Fi you change it with the nose,
just as your router or not, you put it in and you change it, right?
Well, and all this for what?
Look, in 2010 I found the article in which Google went through all,
through all of Spain and all over the world,
precisely by armacenando this value, right?
The BSSID, he knows that sound changes, then, of course,
they put a mult because of private traffic,
but it was not because of taking the BSSID, but it was because of traffic,
but it doesn't matter, right?
He says that if we put Nomapp in our SSID, he does not armacen it.
I did not put it, what armacen?
It doesn't matter.
He will take me on the other hand.
Well, then, can you geolocate by Wi-Fi?
Okay, but in bad hands we can make a man in the middle
and well, and here we don't end today, right?
So what did I do?
Well, look, that was in a polygon.
I scanned all the BSSIDs of the polygon
before it came to the notary, I realized, I said,
let's see, it's true, now I tell you, it's true that there are today
systems that already do it alone, but when I did this, I didn't know it, okay?
That's why I did this jaleo.
We arrived at one of the Malga University, which I used as a reference,
the Malga University was, or was, sorry, it is in a very, very specific place in Malga,
I used it as a reference and everything else,
well, I took the distance and I came up with, well, the formula of distance
existed there, the programs, and you are able to, now I tell you exactly,
what two values ​​you give a very approximate distance, right?
The public
fairytale, what I asked for, sorry, was to check and there was faith in the
provincial that this was a certain distance, it will not be in the GPS,
because if I go to the GPS and there is someone who is dissing me,
it does not serve my provincial, just as something that is as evident as the GPS,
which seems, okay, thank you, which seems that without a movable and movable,
well, I could not base it there, right? Well, the federal, I told him,
look, you have to give faith that on a screen this distance comes out,
with that I conform, it will be my provincial in that distance,
not in the GPS, I did not mention anything, look, this is a 3B Raspberry Pi,
put inside a touch screen, to which I put a GPS, that costs 15 euros or 20 euros,
not more, by the USB port, it recognizes it from the remote control,
what?
No, no, no, but hey, I have that issue of talking about it, right?
Well, anyway, what did I do with Python? How not to use C?
I go crazy and with the notary there, not looking, but he says,
when are we going to be back? I can not tell you within four months,
I have to do something quick, how do I do it quick? I do not know if you can see it,
well, I import what I am going to use, I create a few functions,
this is the function of the Panacea, that is, I found the function,
the function that works, it is true that there is an equation of Maxwell that gives it to you,
I do not know, well, there I will go for two weeks and there I did not find it,
well, in the end, Derek Wartner has his jihava and you have it,
I recognize that it occurred to him, because it worked for me,
there were 50 more if none worked, I mean, but if I have the route at 5 meters,
how is it? Well, that works, you say how many additional functions
that I returned to the frequency of the quality that only the parameters that I needed
obtained the SSID because I had a reference of it, especially when it has a list of a lot of WIFIs,
and what happened? Look, this is another way of doing it,
but I say, for the urgency of doing it, I said, what do I do?
Well, I run a operating system command that puts it in a file and then I read the file,
possibly there are a thousand ways to do this better, much more professional,
but normally in an operating system it is that it does not give you time and you have to go,
it is true that you have a second veil off your pocket, but I say, come on, what works,
let's see what works, when I get jubile I improve it,
I think that will never happen because I always said, when you are a teacher, I improve it,
I improve it, I lie, neither. Well, I already say this, it is the only so strange thing I did,
I emulated the operating system, and well, I simply put it in a, I don't know if it comes from before,
I think I ate it, I have a Whale True, people tell me what a Whale True does,
because it is not an infinite loop, I want it to be showing and mom is recording it,
I say, well, nothing happens, of course it can be in a database, it can do it millions of ways,
yes, yes, it can be improved, but it is that, no, I'm sorry, no.
So, well, look, it is very simple, the truth is that these are my students have already learned
and are saying, when are you going to teach it? I say, come to the PaiKong.
Well, and what I do is call and that I get out of the screen the frequency, the distance
is approximate, I said, look, it is approximate, but well, when you have a lot of approximate distance,
in the end you have a more or less specific location in the circle where all confluents, there.
The notary understood me, look, the notaries today every time more know more about our own,
and he understood me and gave me faith, I paid him, fantastic, because he has ever told me,
I mean, hey, I don't understand this here well and I'm saying, well, I'm going to explain it to you,
I'm going to explain it to you as if it were a judge who is like a three-year-old child and finds out,
I say, fantastic, come on, well, I get a similar result, like this, with the SSID,
I say, similar, I have to tune it, and with the frequency of the signal and with the level of the signal
you can calculate the distance, it is approximate, it is true, it is approximate, but well, I tell you,
if you don't have GPS, if you can't use it, well, even if it is a potato, not a cable connected to the potato
that I give you a signal, right, because the same, well, I have to do this all morning, okay,
I find out that there are services that do more or less the same, but they are not fun,
those who know me from here know that I am like a goat, and they tell me, many times they tell me,
you're going to put the goat, well, I put it, I'm like a goat.
The services, well, Alexander Milynikov has a service, but it doesn't work for me,
it doesn't exist for me, Stars Cop is a Russian web that has us all monitored, be careful,
the same doesn't annex to Russia now, GeoWifi, well, if I go back to the HDMI, okay,
GeoWifi also does it, it is in Python that allows you to obtain it, but I, it is preferable to do it,
I, on my own, and wiggel.net has a fantastic service, I can finish it first,
it has a fantastic service that, to be honest, you can take it on your mobile,
they give you points for being the most wifi-mete, well, I can go back every day,
when I go in the car, I am showing you everything I get, I say,
let's see if I get up from 10,000, because I don't get up, right, there has to be someone who is
traveling every day, but hey, the site is cool, right, let's see, this is hot, it seems that,
well, you look for anything, for a GPS, for a BSSID, whatever you want, there it is,
but I didn't know that, in the press, look, the civil war knows that, well,
I think this man who killed a girl, well, the journalist has no idea,
he talks about three different routes and a Mac address, it's not the Mac address,
it's the BSSID, but the journalists don't know about technology, right, well,
I found it and said, look, the Mac address, well, it's the BSSID,
you have to convey the concept well, you have no idea, well, it seems, remember,
look, when, as a reference, with a celebrity who has used a device,
a mobile, he takes me out 60,000 pages of everything he has done on the mobile,
and what happens, well, it includes the BSSID to which he has tried to connect,
it is fundamental to know that parameter, and people don't know it,
they think it's the name of the Wi-Fi, which is not, no, BSSID,
it's good to always have a GPS in your hand, because if we go less or less
knowing what the coordinates of your site are, and they change it,
then it's that there is some funny thing there, that funny thing can be as,
as I say, as denounceable as the one that, well, because it avoids the radar signal,
I have already told you about it, I don't know if you will take measures or not,
but I tell you, if you go back to the GPS, there is some funny thing that is moving the signal, right?
Then I could say that it is called localization, this talk could be,
as a curiosity, well, we won the trial, the opposite part,
I wanted to attack by the GPS, but there was no GPS,
in front of the judge, they asked me, but why haven't you used the GPS?
I say, because the GPS is there, it's not the case, and in fact, we knew that there is,
in fact, in Malga, it has happened again, yesterday I myself,
a colleague asked me, who also dedicates himself to these foreign halos,
that they have a similar case, and that there is a person in jail because of this,
that is, there is some funny thing in Malga that is capable of changing the location of GPS.
Well, anyway, we won.
My days I do it here, I am in the School of International Management,
trying to transmit all this knowledge that, for a lot of years, I accumulated,
and every day I have more things to tell, right?
And well, thank you very much, and I am at your disposal, you know, my networks,
my LinkedIn, in case there are, I burn, there are many people who know me,
because I burn the networks, I don't know, what I do is transmit,
that knowledge is not left.
And now your turn, one question, I think I'm in time, right?
Thank you very much.
I have a question.
I have a microphone.
This is not a big problem.
Very good.
Can you tell me something about the CSIV casting for you to decide?
Although you use it, someone who goes to the channel can't go to the same place.
Well, I have a lot of networks that don't have a name, or they are just like 0x, 0x, 0x, 0x,
they don't have the same, but the CSIV of the SAC.
Ah, okay, because you can hide it, that yes, you don't have to do it.
And then you have to do it, and then you have to do it.
I had an opportunity, I would go to 80 wifi, I mean, you can be in the middle of the field,
like there are 80.
I take everything I ask, obviously, the more frequent I have, the further I go.
Hello, good morning. Very interesting, I would like to ask, because we pay attention to this,
especially for a personal matter, because wifi is a very sensitive signal to the signal,
and maybe the distance is not according to the potential of the network,
and that can happen to someone who puts a switch on, or just a switch.
Is that the problem you would like to put?
I would like to talk about everything, but not just a wifi, I put myself in a polygon and look at them all,
and I would come all night and all in the morning, because with one night you can't trust,
one day they are putting the window open, because you know that the glass is above the wifi.
So if you are above the office, you have the door open, as it was just in the plan,
well, a lot of wifi comes out, but you have the door and it comes out.
You scan everything, you have to do everything, you have to do everything.
With everything you have a place to control everything, but with one you can't trust,
as it is called, a sample is not reliable, 300, yes.
Any other questions?
I have a question, I know that you know, but I have a question, how do you know if it is a program or how do you do it?
What I do is ask them, I see it works, I see it works to learn something,
but if you want to get a cube, you have to ask me, I see it works.
The cube will arrive quickly and it is a system command.
In this case, you can use the wwlancer, what you see is the device, the Raspberry,
or whatever you want, I have a device, I will try again,
I will say that this is my laptop and whatever, and I just want you to take the four words that I would like,
the SSID, the channel and the reality, simply so that I have it organized.
And I want it to come out in a little thing, here, it comes out.
Then you take the two, there are a thousand ways to do it, you have to know with the hands,
I have done it wrong, you put it in a database, you have it there and you do it in the same way,
you see what you want, there are programs that you do, but I love putting my hand on the computer,
I do not know how to do it, but I do not know how to do it.
In relation to that screen, what is the quality of the data, of the representation
of the frequency and the reaction of the signal, I mean,
because it seems that a person who is a participant does that, the signal, the signal quality is low,
so it is quite simple, for example, a cloudy day, a cloudy day, the signal is also changing,
so it is something that is not ideal.
Of course, but when you go to take samples, you do not take more, as I said,
you do not take more, I go back in the morning, at night, I take several samples,
which in conjunction, as you know, the VSSID does not change, you put it in a database
and then I do a study of that VSSID with all the readings that you have done
and with all the readings, you see how different colors change in the day.
If you take that, you can do your own
to have a close proximity with that and then with the 300 additional readings that you had.
So, with all together, approximately, you had the distance compared to the VSSID
of the base, which is what it is called.
And how reliable is it? I understand that you have been playing for a while,
but really...
How reliable? To me, the VSSID is reliable, but if I do not give it to me...
I understand, but from the point of view of the VSSID, I am not wrong,
so generating networks, of dynamic format, with the same numbers,
that in this area, if you want to do something different,
the VSSID is not something that is impossible.
No, no, of course, it is reliable.
We always use it as a whole.
But I also suppose, on the contrary, that it cannot be done.
There are many ways to get the VSSID, but on the other hand,
they wanted to defend the GPS, and as the GPS could not be used,
I used this.
It could have been thrown away, of course, it could have been thrown away,
but they did not fall into the system.
I went with what I had.
How reliable?
In a judicial system, where the judge has the doubt, he leaves you free.
If you put the judge in his head, he leaves you free.
I used all my means, and he is free.
When he leaves, he falls.
He gave me the mouse and the other mouse.
But if you put it seriously, the other part is not him.
Last question.
Hello, thank you for the presentation.
If you have any questions, if you have any questions,
please send them to the router, that is the ID, the police station.
Because I know that mobile phones, if you have any questions,
the latest generation phones have been used for a whole month.
Change that, that's good.
For us, the use of the user is dangerous,
because you cannot use it for this reason.
If you have a mobile phone, the generation is changing its generation.
Do you have a router that you have used to launch?
I have not yet, but it is also true that a mobile phone that costs a lot.
A router that costs a lot of money, you will not buy it.
It is possible that there are certain
smart phones that are capable of changing that.
It is possible, mobile phones are also going to change that.
I have not found it, but it is possible that within
three or four years this will not be so reliable.
But now we must pass on to who will change their generation.
Someone who has something to hide. The rest of the companies,
which is something that I want to say, but, because they are still having
cyber attacks every day.
As the rest of the companies do nothing, they put on the router
and they put it on, they are the same, because possibly
there is always a path of hope to make them at least know how to do it.
Thank you.
Applause.
Music.