You
My name is Roberto Martínez and I'm going to talk about expert systems in Python with Pino.
The first thing we're going to do is define briefly what an expert system is.
An expert system is a program that contains knowledge in a specific area of an expert.
It is designed to solve complex problems,
reasoning information through rules, instead of doing procedures.
Therefore, it is a different form of programming.
A brief story to give you a context.
In the 1960s, scientists wanted to develop programs that could be developed in some way
and they started developing what is known as GPS or General Problem Solvers,
which are programs that try to solve problems in a generic way.
This approach did not give much results,
so little by little they realized that what they needed was to focus more on specific areas of knowledge
and not try to address generic problems.
In the 1970s, they started developing the first expert systems that focus more on specific problems
and in the 1980s they became very popular.
There were very successful projects that some still use today,
such as Dendral, Mycine and Mistral, which are expert systems,
and technology was very promising.
So, well, the entire industry wanted to get into the car of artificial intelligence,
and that almost never worked out well.
In the early 90s, these very promising systems appeared in the very beginning of the 90s,
and they became very difficult to maintain,
and the investors began to stop investing in artificial intelligence.
That led us to what is known as the winter of artificial intelligence,
where, well, let's say, it stopped betting on this type of system.
Expert systems are still being used today, but only in much more specific problems.
Well, let's take a look at the panorama we have in Paizo as a matter of expert systems,
which is, to be honest, a bit disappointing.
We have two more or less well-known libraries, PyClips,
which is a wrapper to use clips directly in Python,
clips for those of you who don't know them,
which is a language for the creation of expert systems,
and this wrapper, PyClips, has been used since 2008,
and, well, it is compatible with recent versions,
only for Python 2.4, Python 2.5.
The other package known to you is called Pyke.
It is pure Python, but it is inspired by Prolog.
It is not exactly...
It is not exactly designed to make expert systems,
and the last one is in 2010, so it is not particularly maintained.
So, because of this panorama and, among other things,
it was created by PyNo.
APPLAUSE
How wonderful you are!
Well, what is PyNo?
PyNo is a library to write expert systems in Python, inspired by clips.
What are clips and what is PyNo?
Clips, as I said before, are a proper programming language,
not Python, it is a language for expert systems.
It has a long journey, born in 1985 in NASA,
and it continues to develop today,
so it is a very, very mature software.
It has, obviously, a fairly large base of users,
and it is even used as reference implementation
for other expert systems.
What is PyNo?
PyNo is a library or library for the creation of expert systems in Python.
It was developed in 2015, inspired by clips.
It is a pure Python, and that gives us certain benefits,
like it is an object and we can use the power of Python
in the different stages of the expert system,
and obviously it has much more limited inferences than clips.
We are going to give a super-accelerated course to PyNo,
because PyNo is quite intense and we have only 20 minutes.
I don't know if you can see the architecture there, I don't know if you can see it.
Projector is... No.
There it is.
There? It is visible?
Yes.
Well, the architecture of PyNo is divided into three fundamental parts.
The first is the work memory, which contains the current state of the system's inferences,
based on the facts that have been declared, the rule base,
which contains the knowledge of the system,
and it is a set of rules that are programmed,
they have been programmed, and the interpreter,
which is what provides the library,
and what makes the execution of the program run,
is that the rules that are satisfied by the facts that have been declared,
and the work memory.
It is important to differentiate the knowledge,
what is defined by the knowledge,
and what is defined by the information here.
The knowledge is the rules,
it is a set of rules,
if this happens, then I do that,
and the work memory is simply that information,
the bread costs 1 euro, or whatever.
The knowledge motor.
Can you see it?
Yes.
The knowledge motor.
Well, the knowledge motor provides the interface
to interact with the expert system.
It has references to the rest of the elements of the system.
In the example you can see a knowledge motor being executed,
but it has no rules, so obviously it does nothing.
It is simply a class created by Noble Chenjain.
The facts, what are the facts?
As I said before, the information unit that handles the system
is represented by the class Fact,
and Fact is a dictionary,
that is, a dict, and it is a dictionary a little special.
In addition to accepting keys and values as a normal dictionary,
it can also be passed values without a key,
and then it behaves like a kind of list.
These two behaviors can be given at the same time.
Therefore, if you look at the example...
I don't know if you can see here...
No...
If you can see here,
that three values are passed to the fact that
X, Y, and Z are passed without keys,
and then two values with a key.
There you go.
And then they recover, in the case of the first values,
the first is a list, and the second is a dictionary.
It is also recommended...
It is recommended to make de-fact subclasses
to...
to be able to represent different types of information.
Here in the second example you can see
that there is a class of fact called alert,
and then we are using it to define alerts.
Well, red type alerts,
or there we have another fact,
which is state, which is a kind of criticism.
The rules.
The rules are the most important element that Pino has,
since what represents us is knowledge.
The rule consists of actions that will be carried out
if necessary conditions are given.
All the rules have basically two parts.
The antecedent, which is also called left-hand side,
and the consequence, or right-hand side.
The antecedent consists of a set of conditions,
and the consequence is a series of actions.
In Pino, a rule is declared by decorating a method
with the rule decorator.
Or rule, if you know how to pronounce it.
Here, for example, we are generating a rule,
which, as a condition in the left-hand side,
has an alert,
and in the consequence,
we have simply a method that will be executed.
And when the alert comes out,
it will print this.
Ok, rules, the comparison of patterns.
As I said before, in the antecedent
we can express conditions to execute the rule.
These conditions can define
the different states of the memory of work.
What can be defined within an antecedent?
The facts that must be in the memory,
and the values that must have those facts
to be fulfilled.
The keys that must have, the values within the keys,
and we can even say that different facts
have to share the same value,
regardless of the value that is.
PINO provides the tools to express
any type of restriction.
Logical operators, like ANT or NOT,
restrictions for fields,
for example, like DINES, which matches any value,
literal values, it has to be exactly this value,
or filtered functions.
And there you need to set a function,
and if that function returns true,
it will fulfill the condition.
In addition, these logical operations
about the restrictions of fields
can be mixed with logical operations.
We can say that this function has to be filtered,
or it has to be this exact value.
For example,
if I manage to see it,
we have that this rule, the first,
what it asks is that in the memory of work
there are two facts.
One is called shirt,
with a color key,
and I don't know if you can read this.
With the color key,
we are giving it an internal name, which is C,
I don't know if you can see it there,
which says match.C.
And also, that value has to be one of these two literals.
The L means literal,
and it says blue, or here we have the operator,
or gray, okay?
This will match in the memory of work,
whenever there is a shirt type with the color,
blue or gray.
And it also has to happen that in the same memory of work,
we have a pattern type,
with the color key,
and exactly with the same value
that we have on the other side,
because we are matching and assigning to the variable of C.
If this happens, this rule will be launched,
and that C that we have captured
will be passed as an argument.
And that is the color column of color C.
In the second rule,
we need a shirt type,
with a price key,
and that price must meet this expression,
okay?
It is a lambda and simply that the P is between 10 and 25.
We are looking for a shirt
with that price range,
and if we find it, we always do.
And the last one,
well, I can't see it.
The last one,
we are looking for a shirt
with a price that we are going to call P,
we are going to filter it with another filtered function,
in this case, which is less than 30 euros,
and we also need a budget type fact,
we are going to capture the value
that has that fact and budget,
we are going to call it P,
we are going to do an additional check
with the variable P and the variable T,
and whenever P is less than T,
that is, the price of the shirt is within our budget,
then this is going to happen.
And this function is going to be called,
let's see,
it is going to be called the function
that simply imprisons it.
Okay, the execution cycle.
Do you see it all?
Yes?
And this is going to start with the main program,
which is the program that we write,
the first thing it does is to instantiate the knowledge engine
that we are going to create,
this Noble Chen-Cheng that we talked about before.
Then, that main program is going to call the Routine Reset,
which will reinitiate the working memory
so that everything is clean, for the following execution,
and if we have any initial fact,
any fact that we want to declare at the beginning,
it will also be declared.
The last thing it has to do,
is that it has this cycle,
which basically what it does is
to look for the rules of our engine
that are matching with the working memory,
and put them in a list that is called Agenda.
That agenda is simply the list of rules that you have to launch.
Then it orders it with an internal algorithm
that is called conflict resolution,
and simply, look if that list is empty.
If it is empty, we have finished,
and we return to the main program.
If it is not empty,
if it is not empty, we execute the first rule,
and that rule, as we have written,
probably modifies the working memory in some way,
then everything has to be recalculated.
If you look like this,
there are new rules to execute,
and the first one is executed again.
This cycle continues until there is nothing left to execute.
Let's see a practical example.
This is a program that we are going to do with PINOW,
and whose goal is to generate discount coupons
for a store.
The system has three objectives.
The first objective is to encourage new customers' purchases
in the establishment.
The second objective is to increase the consumption of other products
that they have not bought,
and the third objective is to increase the consumption of products
with more profit margin.
The interface we have is very simple.
The program's input will be a list of the products
that the customer has bought,
and the output, the list of coupons that we want to print
so that in their next purchase they can use them.
Let's see the code.
Can it read well?
Yes.
Yes?
Yes, it goes down there.
Oh, no, no.
Here we have a small summary of the program we want to do,
the objectives and the outputs.
The first thing we are going to do is import PINOW,
and we are going to declare the facts we are going to handle
during this program.
In this case, the first thing we need is something
to manage the input and output,
the products, which is the input,
and the coupons, which are the output.
We simply make a subclass of facts,
and with this we will represent the information.
We also need two additional facts,
which are the promotions that are obvious in the store,
and another where we are going to have the information
of the benefit we get from each product.
In this way we can calculate, if we are more interested,
increase the sale of another.
They are already declared.
We are going to try to make an expert system for the first objective.
The first objective was to encourage new purchases
of the customer in the establishment.
What we are going to do for this is generate coupons
of type 2x1, 3x2, etc.
Is there the code?
Yes?
As I said, we are doing a class
that inherits Nauldets and Jain
to make a motor of knowledge.
Besides, I have not told you
any method that we decorate with the fact decorator
will be called at the beginning when we make a reserve,
and what we will do is to produce the initial facts
that we want to put into the work memory.
In our case, as we want to generate promotions of type 2x1,
what we are going to put into the work memory
are the promotions that are there.
In this case, we have promotion of type 2x1
for the product, 2x1 for despalcual,
3x2 for triple-pills.
This will go to the work memory
and this other method,
which is decorated with the rule decorator,
allows us to make a rule.
In this case, what are we doing?
We are looking for a work memory
of promotion type,
which has a key called type
and we are going to assign it the name of variable t.
In addition, this type has to fulfill
this predicated, this London function.
This is something else that we are looking for
with a return.
We are looking for the type to be number x, number.
In addition, this promotion type
has to have a product key
with a value and we are going to call that value p.
The second thing we are looking for in the work memory
is that there is a product that has the same name,
sorry, that has the key name with that same value p.
For this to work, this p and this p have to be the same.
If I have in the work memory a promotion object
and a product object that has a certain name
and they are different, it will not match.
They have to be the same. That is the restriction.
In the case that this two elements are in the work memory
that we are looking for, this function is going to be called
and the p and the p that we are capturing will be passed.
In this case, what we do is simply declare a new work memory,
that a type T coupon is generated with product p.
We are going to execute it.
We are going to use the function watch to see what is happening below.
It will simply log in and out of the engine.
We install the engine,
we restart the work memory
and here we see that certain facts are put into the memory,
which we have defined in our default.
We are going to declare a couple of products that the client has bought.
Some do docks, mineral water and batteries.
Now we are going to execute the engine.
What is seen here is that the rules are being executed,
the rule of type FERTA-NM,
and coupons are generating us.
If we want to see what the work memory is,
we can use the attribute of facts.
This will print the memory list.
Here you see that two coupons have been generated.
The objective 1 seems to be completed.
The objective number 2 is the consumption of other products.
For this, what we are going to do is generate discount packs.
If the user has bought, for example,
a fray and we have a pack that is fray plus mopa,
with 25% discount,
in the case that he has bought one of the two products,
but not the two,
we are going to generate that discount for the next purchase.
We generate the vigent promotions,
in this case, two packs,
and the rule that we have here is that if there is a promotion of a pack,
for a product P1 and P2, with a certain discount,
that is seen here,
and one of these two conditions happens,
that is, that the product has not been bought 1,
but the product has been bought 2,
or the product has been bought 1, but not 2,
because it is a XOR of all life,
then this function is going to be called,
and the function generates a new coupon.
We instantiate, restart,
here we see all the facts,
and generate the two products that the user has bought.
We run the engine,
and the rules skip,
we generate the coupons,
and we are done.
We are going to check another case,
and if we buy the two products, we do not generate the coupon,
because we would be losing money,
we are not incentivizing anything.
The products of the same pack, we run,
nothing happens.
The goal number 3 is the consumption of products
with more profit margin.
To accomplish this, what we do is that we have a list
of the benefits we have for the product,
and if a product has been bought of a typology,
for example, beer, that leaves us less margin
than another type of beer we have,
we are going to give a coupon discount
for that beer with more margin.
Here, for example, we declare that for the MAU beer
we have a benefit of 0.5,
and for the accented beer, a benefit of 0.9.
Obviously, if the client buys MAU,
we want him to buy accented beer.
The rule, what it tells us is that if the product has been bought of a P1,
and we have a benefit for P1,
that we are going to call it G1,
and then it turns out that another benefit for a product P2,
and they are of the same type.
And we see that the profits of the first,
sorry, of the second, are greater than the profits of the first,
we want this rule to be released.
In that case, when the rule is released,
what we are going to do is,
we are going to take the difference from the profits,
and we are going to generate a discount coupon for half.
We continue to earn, although it is half.
We instantiate, restart the work memory,
introduce the facts,
and declare that the user has bought MAU beer.
To execute.
No time?
No.
Well, basically that's all.
What I wanted to tell you,
and finally, that you can put the three engines together in one engine,
and give it a more friendly interface.
What we are doing here is a function,
because this is still Python,
where we put all the product names,
and it will generate all the coupons.
Here we are using it,
and finally it generates these coupons.
And that's it, no more time.
Thank you very much, Roberto.
There is no time for questions,
but if you want, you can go down to the white board,
and we will have someone to ask me if I can do it.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.