You
thisyo
The PICON are conferences around the PyZone programming language
and the PICON is in particular that national level conference
that takes place in Spain every year, being this the fifth edition we make.
Every year we try to take the PICON to some different cities in Spain.
We start in Madrid, Zaragoza, Valencia, Almería and this year Cáceres.
We go all over Spain, the idea is to get to the best people
and it is organized both by the Association of PICON in Spain and by a local group.
The idea is that we all get together and talk about the PICON.
We all come to share our experience, our knowledge
and we will spend a while and get to know each other.
It is like Christmas, but for computer scientists.
Hello, we are OpenSystems, a Spanish company
specialized in open source technology and very focused on big data,
machine learning, data analysis.
We are in PyCon because we love to contribute with open source communities,
mainly with Python, which is one of the technologies we use the most.
We have contact with the developers and users of this technology.
It is the third year that we contribute as sponsors
and we will continue to do so in the future.
Python is a programming language.
Normally, Python scientists say that it comes with the batteries
because it is used for a lot of things.
It is very easy to use, the barrier to entry is very small,
so you can find it in a lot of places.
It is used to learn, it is used in many companies,
it is my company that we use.
It is very easy to start programming in Python
and there are many tools already developed.
For me, the great thing about Python is the community.
We are celebrating here.
If you have a problem, I am sure there is someone who will call you
and say, I want to program this, I will help you and I will teach you.
I came to this event because I am very interested in the Python community
and everything that is being done here.
I have come here because it is an annual meeting that we have.
I have already given a workshop yesterday of TensorFlow
with how to predict death in the game of thrones
and this afternoon I will talk about how to make command lines with click.
For us as Ticotea, this event is our home.
We have been participating in the last years and not only coming here
to meet engineers like those we have within the company
but also to share what we do, our projects, our ambition,
our ideas, the new developments that we are thinking
and have the feeling of community and being able to share with everyone.
Why Gacere?
Why Gacere? It is a good question.
The truth is that it is something curious because all the previous organizations
have been a local team that was what is a site in the site.
Here the truth is that we were all out and that has made it a little more difficult
but we were counting on the help of the university
and that has made us all this easier.
The local team of Gacere was tied to the head and said
well, in Gacere and they encouraged, they set up a spectacular proposal,
the site is spectacular, so nothing,
here we are to meet Gacere and have fun at the weekend.
I liked the event because we do a lot of networking,
you know other companies that do other projects,
you find out about things that exist, new developments
and the truth is that we consider it as an important event
within the year, within the company of the two brands
and we try to collaborate as sponsors every year.
We are André Ebruy, we are a team of English with a Malaga headquarters,
we are already on the team of the Malaga team,
we are in charge of doing the transition from Divisa to the 3D Final.
Last year we started sponsoring the Pycones in Almería,
this year we have repeated and we try to repeat later too.
We also sponsor the group Malaga Paizcon,
since a couple of years ago.
What we are currently looking for are profiles,
Paizcon and DevOps,
if you are interested, you can come with us.