So, yeah, without further ado then let's welcome Vasia.
Hello everyone and thank you for coming.
Is the sound okay?
Can you hear me okay?
Okay.
Thanks very much for coming and thank you to the organizers for having us here and welcome
to fail fast ML ops.
So just a little note before I begin.
At intelligence we use Python for pretty much all machine learning projects that we do.
For this talk we're mostly going to be talking about more high level concepts so in case
anybody is interested in deploying machine learning solutions in any other language,
hopefully it will be just as relevant.
So with that let's begin and I like to start by deconstructing a little bit the title because
we have some terms there that people might understand with different meanings.
So first of all fail fast.
Many of you will be familiar with this phrase.
I may have heard it before.
Fail fast is a guiding principle that prioritizes fast execution over perfect execution.
So the idea is if I spent too long trying to perfect my solution before putting it out
there into the world, the situation may have changed and by the time it's deployed it may
no longer be fully relevant or as relevant as intended.
And so according to the fail fast principle the idea is it's best to deploy the first
iteration as fast as possible and then iterate based on the feedback received.
Next up ML ops.
I include here a quote from Google where I'd like to highlight a couple of aspects from
their influential article on ML ops.
So first of all ML ops as they highlight here is the first in ML engineering culture
and practice.
So we're not talking about specific set of technologies or a specific role on machine
learning projects.
It's about the culture and practice.
And the second aspect, so two specific process to highlight.
So automation and monitoring at all steps of the construction of a machine learning system.
So in practical terms the term ML ops tends to be used a little bit more broadly as well
to refer to a wider set of good practices when it comes to developing and deploying
machine learning solutions.
Especially those that help to smooth the transition between the development and the operation
side of things in production.
So ML ops as such is an enormous field.
It covers a huge amount of ground.
And don't worry about not being able to read any text on this diagram.
But it's a figure from a recent review that I'm happy to provide a reference later on.
I think the reference just falls off the bottom of the slide.
But so what we see here is starting off from the very beginning of the initiating the project,
the analysis of the business goals and so on, going through the requirements, feature
engineering pipeline development, on to the experimentation phase where we do what we
typically associate us with the breadth and budget of data science work, developing our
models, validating them and so on.
And then onwards to feature stores, work flow orchestration and automated machine learning
work flow pipelines.
And then all of this is tied together.
See here at the bottom, through monitoring and feedback loops.
It's a vast field and it would be presumptuous to think we can do justice in 30 minutes,
but also given our limited experience with, we don't have experience with all of this.
So I selected two aspects for the talk.
So we'll dwell on the experimentation part of the process, specifically around model
training and validation, where I like to talk specifically about the concepts of traceability
and reproducibility.
And then after that, we'll move on to the production and we'll talk about monitoring
and feedback loops specifically, so the concepts of observability and feedback.
And yeah, over there, underwriter Zalemzian just illustrating the wide variety of different
roles that are involved at the various stages of the process.
And then finally, last bit of the title, lessons learned.
So we're not here to teach anyone a lesson.
We're here very much to learn ourselves.
And so once we have gained a little bit of experience over the past few years, having
had lots of opportunities to fail and improve, we're very much here to learn.
And so whatever your perspective and your experience from ML Ops would be really best
to hear from you.
So do please reach out after the talk.
Okay.
So with that, let's begin.
And let's talk about traceability and reproducibility.
So a lot of data scientists, machine learning engineers, and myself included, we started
our data science journey through notebooks that like you interspersed the code with the
results that it produces.
And notebooks are a fantastic tool for lots of things, for teaching, for learning, for
exploration and prototyping and so on.
But when it comes to developing solutions for production, if your workflow is too heavily
dependent on notebooks, it can lead to difficulties when it comes to the concept of traceability.
And why is that?
So I'm sure data scientists in the room here will appreciate that without me having to
tell you.
So whenever you're creating a candidate solution, you have all of these different components
that go into it.
And you have your input data set.
You write your code for preprocessing it.
You write your model training code and choose your specific set of hyperparameters for it.
And a unique combination of those will produce a unique result and a unique candidate solution.
What happens in the real world?
All of these components go through a lot of different iterations.
So for example, you may have to discard a certain part of data because a certain subset
is just not suitable for the project.
And you may iterate all of those other components that go into it.
And so before you know it, you have results in hand that maybe you find it very hard to
trace how exactly you got them.
And let's say, for example, that you shared your results with excited business stakeholders
and two weeks later, they come to you, oh, we really love seeing those results.
But could you run it just changing that one tiny little detail?
And if in the meantime, you iterate it 10 or 15 times on your code, you might find it
very hard to reproduce exactly what you did two weeks ago.
And it can be even more difficult if the results that we're talking about were not produced
by yourself.
But maybe there was a colleague who worked on that project.
Maybe that was a year ago.
Maybe they loved the company since then.
So given all these considerations, larger amounts of work can be rendered useless in
the absence of good traceability and reproducibility.
So the solution to all of this, of course, involves versioning everything that you can
version.
So I know that you'll be familiar with some or many of the tools highlighted here.
So Git and DVC and MLflow for versioning not just code, but data sets and your models
and your model results.
And there was a talk earlier today, which I suppose many of you would have seen on MLflow,
to introduce MLflow for experiment tracking and registering models, which was excellent.
If you're not familiar with experiment tracking with an established framework such as MLflow,
I would really encourage you to give it a go and MLflow is a great place to start.
One thing that I would like to talk about today is the concept of linking the results
that you track with a tool like MLflow with the exact version of the code that was used
to produce it.
And specifically, the way that we do this is by using Git tags as triggers for our model
training runs on a CI CD platform.
So if you run your model training on a CI CD platform like GitHub Actions, for example,
as shown here, you can configure it in such a way that the pipeline is triggered whenever
you push a certain tag.
So the example here shows a convolutional neural network training that gets triggered
every time that I push to the repo, a tag that follows this pattern, train CNN.
And then for my experiment tracking code, I can extract the tag from the environment
and pass it on as a tag to my experiment tracking tool such as MLflow.
And so as a consequence, when I go to my MLflow board to see all the results, we can see
all the metrics resulting from a run and higher up, all the parameters that were tracked
with the same run.
For every one of those runs, we can see a Git tag that's associated with this run.
So it seems like a part of the screen is cut off.
Is there something we can do about the resolution, perhaps?
Sorry, I didn't notice that earlier.
Yeah, I think that's better.
Yeah, I think that's good.
A little bit smaller, but I think that's okay.
Fantastic, thank you.
So I'm not sure if you're able to read, but so on MLflow, that is the experiment tracking
board where for every experiment that we run, we have a time stamp and we'll have all the
associated metrics and parameters that were used with that run.
And the point I'm making here is that if we pass the Git tag to MLflow, we can then get
the, for any experiment that we have run in the past, we can return to the exact same
version of the code that produced it.
And even better, the fact of running all our training runs on a CICD platform offers a
possibility to just relaunch any pass-trans just at a click of a button because the platforms
tend to have this relaunch button at a single click.
So if we return to the same example of a colleague of ours that may have left the company a year
ago, I'm no longer at the mercy of having to, you know, depend on whatever documentation
they left behind.
But now we can just go to their MLflow board and find the best run based on the metrics
and that leads us straight via the Git tag to be able to reproduce their experiments.
Okay, so these concepts of traceability and reproducibility really permeate the way that
we've designed our experimentation environment with which we work.
And I'll talk you through how it's constructed.
So everything runs in a Kubernetes cluster.
And here on the top you see we have the user tools within which individual users, mostly
the data scientists, will develop their solutions in notebooks and using an IT like VS code.
And they're connected with the data store via Migno, so connecting through to S3.
And there are two, so this offers a flexible environment like a sandbox, like a playground,
full flexibility for the users.
But there are two intentional limitations.
First of all, they have limited persistence.
And secondly, they don't have right permissions back to the data store.
Why is that?
So it's intended such that it removes the temptation for me to, if I've just developed
a model through some quick experimentation or constructed a new proposal data set, it
prevents me from storing it under a name that I've just invented into the data store without
leaving a trace that can be used by my colleagues to then track where that data set or that
model came from.
So whenever I have something that I consider is worth persisting, I have to go through the
path that I described earlier.
I have to push a tag that will launch a workflow that I defined to the code repository and
that will then trigger the CI CD server to launch a series of jobs, well, the workflow
for the training.
And the intern will connect with the MLflow tracking server.
So the consequence of working in this way is that any produced artifacts through our
experimentation can always be traced back to their origin.
Okay.
So for the rest of the talk, I'd like to switch gears and move to the production environment
and speak specifically about the concepts of observability and feedback and tell you
a couple of stories from our own projects along the way.
And I'd like to begin this section with a little thought experiment.
So imagine that you're in charge of hospitals in a certain town, right?
And you're tasked with improving the treatment for a certain condition, it's called a condition
X.
And you have resources available to do so, but you have to choose from one of the three
available hospitals.
And you know about these hospitals that one of them has an 80% recovery rate for the patients
treated there.
And I don't have only 60% recovery rate.
And for hospital C, there's no data available.
Which one will you choose to allocate more resources?
Most people will say the hospital with the best known recovery rate, the one with 80%,
and ignore the one with no data.
So it can be a real shame if it turns out that the hospital that we didn't know anything
about turns out to be the best one, has fantastic doctors, fantastic facilities, but they just
don't have a very good administration department and they don't submit their reports on time.
What's the point of this story, right?
I'm bringing that because I think it has parallels to machine learning solutions in the sense
that we can have a perfect machine learning solution running in production.
In the absence of good observability, it can serve a little purpose because the people
who depend on it, the people who need to make decisions, aren't able to make informed decisions
because of not being able to see those outputs.
So that's on the importance of observability.
And I'd like to share a little story from one of our own projects.
So the visibility is not very good, but it's not, it's not, the details don't matter.
We ran a project for a telecommunications company that was, so the idea of the solution
that we put in production there was to automate the processing of emails coming in through
to their customer service department.
It was an email classification service.
And so here on the dashboard, you might be able to see a timeline of the request and
the responses.
So what happened on this project was we were being very careful to cover our solution with
automated testing, had a bunch of unit tests, production tests, integration tests.
And it was running fairly, you know, running stably on the side of the solution that was
aimed at generating the predictions.
But the part of the solution for observability, we didn't pay so much attention.
And so invariably there came an upgrade where we, with the upgrade, we broke the dashboards,
we broke the observability.
And intuitively thinking, perhaps naively thinking, you might not pay so much attention
because, you know, if you log to, if you connect via the console to observe what's happening
with your solution in production, you can still see responses coming in, you can still
see predictions going out, and you may be comforted.
Well, things are running as they should be running and we'll just get on with fixing
the dashboards in our own time.
But from the point of view of the business stakeholder, from the product owner, that
can be a very frustrating experience because they're left blind and they're not able to
make any from decisions from this based on the processes they have running in production.
So what we learned from this experience is that observability has to be treated as a
first-class citizen.
It can't be treated as an afterthought.
And so the observability code requires the same amount of love and attention and testing
and test coverage as the rest of your machine learning code.
So far we've been talking about, you know, observing the requests and responses and so
on.
But another thing that's really interesting to know is whether those predictions are
correct or not, right?
We need to know whether the patients are not just coming into the hospital and going out
of it.
We need to know a week later, did they recover, did they get worse.
And so I'd like to move to speaking about the concept of feedback.
So in this particular case, as I mentioned, it was an email classification project.
So we're going from the incoming email through various steps of processing and a couple
of different models to produce an output, which is one of the four different classes.
And the emails could be associated with, for example, a request to conduct some repairs,
maybe related to billing or new orders or change.
And the process that they had in place before we deployed our solutions to automate a part
of that process went like this.
So the incoming email would arrive and it would go to operators who would manually categorize
them according to which of the four classes it belonged to.
And depending on the class, depending on the tag that they give to the email, it would
go to the correct processing queue.
And then within each of those correct departments, they would open a ticket that would then go
on to the correct people to address the issue that the customer brought up.
And so our solution set at this point of the process.
So now instead of a person looking manually and sorting all these emails, it would go
to our solution.
So this is the point here in a Kubernetes cluster.
And the inference workflow here would receive the email, run all that preprocessing and
classification, and return the predicted email tag at the same time as then storing the prediction
and the influx database for live monitoring and the chronograph dashboards.
And so in order to know whether the predictions are correct or not, the idea is we need to
go a step later in the process where we can extract the information.
And in this case, we have to look at the tickets generated because tickets always carry an
email ID that lets us identify the email on which they were based.
And so if we predicted for a certain email that it's a repair email, and then it turns
out that a change ticket was opened from that same email, then we have to record that as
a wrong prediction.
And otherwise if we predicted repair and the ticket is of type repair, then all is good
and we record it as a correct prediction.
And so in parallel with our inference workflow, here we have the feedback workflow, which
is receiving the tickets for feedback, and then it's storing the performance metrics
in influx DB that go onto the dashboards, and it's storing all of those data points,
and the feedback, the correct labels from the tickets in among the DB.
And that there is available for us to run a retraining and then plug an updated retraining
classifier back into the inference workflow.
So one interesting thing that happened in this particular project was we thought, well,
we developed our model first, and then we think about feedback later.
So once we had the inference workflow developed, we found ourselves in a situation where we
didn't dare to deploy it, we didn't dare to activate our service without having the feedback
in place, given all the considerations about observability, we didn't want to operate blind
because if critical processes are involved, you could be getting it wrong and not having
that fast feedback to iterate on it.
And so what we ended up having to do in this project was we had our inference code just
sitting there for a few weeks making predictions, but not acting on them whilst we were developing
the feedback workflow to catch up.
So what we learned from this experience is at least in some situations, it can be very
useful to think about developing your feedback workflow first.
And it actually has a couple of different advantages.
So I mean, it's in line with the fast-fill approach whereby you get your feedback as quickly
as possible and you can iterate quickly.
It helps you avoid that early stage where you might be operating blind without having
that feedback from the environment, from, I say, the business application and so on.
But also, another upshot of this approach is it lets you collect the data from the live
production environment, which in many cases can be quite different from data that you
might be given to develop your model in the first place.
I don't know how many of you might have been given a data set by somebody saying, you know,
this is a very nicely carefully curated, carefully selected data set.
It's very clean, so use that to develop your model.
Having had experience of developing models like that that work great in the laboratory,
but then reliably fall over on their nose as soon as you expose them to the data from
the real world, it's much nicer to be able to collect all the data in the environment
where the model will actually be encountering.
So that you're not developing your model based on some distributions that are completely
different from the ones that it will see in production.
Okay, so that brings me to conclusions.
Just to wrap up, the main messages with respect to traceability and reproducibility in the
experimentation phase of MLOPs.
One thing that we think helps us a lot with these concepts is using CICD workflows to
run our experiments.
And we tend to trigger them by using Git tags as triggers for the CICD workflows.
You could achieve the same with Git commits and so on, but we find Git tags just help
a little bit with keeping it organized and so on.
And then when it comes to observability and feedback, observability code is a first class
citizen.
It's treated as an afterthought and it can be really helpful to at least consider deploying
the feedback code before deploying the model.
So with quickly skimmed over, MLOPs, a couple of concrete parts of it, but that's only
just scratching the surface.
There's a lot more there to explore.
But maybe just one concluding thought.
A lot of people who speak to, you know, clients, managers, and so on, may still have that preconception
that putting a model in production effectively just means, oh, I'll develop my model in a
notebook and then wrap an API around it.
But in reality, there's so much more that needs to go into a mature machine learning
system in production.
And in fact, if you were looking for that model serving code on that diagram, you'll
find it corresponds to just that one tiny little block on the edge.
So yeah, I hope some of that has been useful.
And as I said earlier, do please reach out and get in touch.
And thank you very much for your attention.
Thank you very much for your talk.
Do we have any questions in the audience?
If you remember, you can make it the question in English, Spanish, Portuguese, I don't know.
Any questions?
No?
Well, let me, maybe, maybe, well, I don't know.
I just be loud.
Okay.
Yeah, that's a good question.
We moved away from training in local.
So we tend to train on CSD platform.
I know that you can use MLflow for experiment tracking and just deploy the MLflow application
on your local machine and run it there.
So I think in terms of collaborating as a team, it helps to move it to a CSD platform
individually.
It may be possible.
I don't know.
I don't have a clear answer to that, but you can certainly use MLflow to give you that
traceability aspect.
And if you're working alone on a project, that's probably good enough.
What is your recommendation to improve the quality of the code that data science normally
produces?
That's a good question.
So a few different things.
So one thing that we tend to do within our teams, can you hear me okay?
So we tend to do a fair amount of code review.
So we'll review each other's code.
And sometimes just being in that different mindset of saying, oh, I mean, the role of
reviewing somebody's code and you may just take that little bit more attention to think
about good practices than when you're coding on your own and in a hurry.
So that's one mechanism.
Static code analysis tools as well.
So various...
You're talking about file linters?
Yeah, automated linters, formators.
And what's the name of the...
Sonar cloud.
That's the one.
Yes.
So I don't know if you're familiar with Sonar cloud, but it's a...
Yeah.
So yeah, I would say a combination of these various approaches.
Also insisting that...
Sorry.
I think maybe there's a cultural component there as well because in certain teams, it's
expected that data scientists will just write the quickest code that will get a model trained
and maybe setting expectations within your team if that really makes it very hard for
the people who then have to productionize their code, maybe some cultural aspects there
in the conversation about code quality can help.
Do we have another question in the audience?
In the meantime, I can tell you about...
Hello.
I think it's a good approach to analyze the data scientist team from the operation team,
like they use the MLflow tracking server and the operational team use node that there are
some models there and can use them wherever they need.
It's a good approach.
Thanks for the question.
Good question.
Maybe there are situations when it's good to have that separation.
In our project, we like to keep people working a little bit more closely together.
So typically, machine learning engineers and data scientists will work together through
different phases of the project and that can be helpful both for the data scientists to
appreciate what the machine learning engineers will have to think about later on, productivizing
the solutions and the other way around, maybe.
There are certain...
I can give you an example from one of our projects to put a bit more weight on this point.
So there was a model that had a specific role of the operations, maybe some filtering, some
normalizations, and then some other mathematical operations.
And later on, when we looked at the production code, it turned out that at some point, the
order of two operations was changed.
And in some cases, it doesn't matter, but in some cases, it matters a whole lot.
And so if you have a strong separation between your experimentation, exploration, and data
science team and the people putting it in production, you maybe raise the risk of having
these sort of incidents happen.
So based on my experience, I would say it's usually better to have it a little bit less
separated and a little bit more communicated.
But maybe in some situations, a clear separation is useful.
We have any time.
It's working, yes.
There will be the last, so.
And if someone wants to ask, in Castellano, it's no problem.
In your day-to-day, how do you work and struggle with the difference between the data in development
and production?
Especially with the, I'm not talking about maybe to watch about the data screen or not,
but what the data expires because you need newer data, because it's very time series-related.
How do you work with the difference?
So you test your models and you know that it won't be an issue when you deploy?
That's a very good question.
And in fact, we're on a journey to be able to do that better.
So currently we have too much of a separation between the laboratory data and the production
data and that loop of connecting the two, of establishing that symmetry between the experimental
environment and production environment.
We don't have it fully connected and fully set up and automated, so it's still a little
bit manual to create new data sets for training based on production data.
So I'm afraid I can't give you a very satisfying answer there, but if anyone has experience
on this topic, it'll be really nice to have a conversation about that.
And that was the last question.
So let's thank or speak it again.
Okay, thank you very much.