Hello, I am Davide Fioco and I will be talking about serving machine learning models with
web applications developed using two cool Python libraries, Streamlit and FastAPI.
If you want to write me afterwards, this is my Twitter handle.
It sounds a bit funny in Spanish, I know.
I didn't know back then when I chose it.
In a way, I think it's easy to remember, so maybe that's useful.
About me, I started using Python now more than 10 years ago.
I was using it to analyze data coming from computer simulations or physical systems.
My background is indeed physics and currently I'm a senior data scientist at Frontiers.
I will spend some time talking about Frontiers.
Frontiers is an open access scientific publisher.
So we have this website www.frontiers.org and scientists can send their work in the form
of scientific articles to our website.
And afterwards, the articles are reviewed by other experts in the same field.
And if they pass the peer review, they are eventually published online.
Currently, we have 92 journals online that are open for submissions and Frontiers has
published so far 171,000 articles.
I was looking into this yesterday and if you look for Python, well, programming, just to
distinguish it from snakes.
We have indeed scientific articles that are dealing with the usage of Python in science.
So applications in biology or libraries that are used in a scientific domain.
So if you're interested, check it out.
Something else about us, we are over 500 employees in different offices in the world.
There's one engineering office in Madrid and the company currently processes over 60,000
scientific articles per year.
This is pretty labor intensive.
And therefore we have a technology stock that also uses Python.
We use Python mainly in our big data pipelines and to power our machine learning components
in the platform.
So yeah, we'll be talking about machine learning.
And as you know already, it's a very powerful technology.
At work, we use natural language processing to machine learning to process text data.
For instance, to classify scientific articles based on their content.
In this slide, you find an example, which is sentiment analysis.
Here we want to classify sentences based on their mood.
Granada is really beautiful.
It's a happy sentence.
So we'll have an algorithm which is able to recognize this.
Actually if you visit this repository by Hug & Face, there's even algorithms that are able
to read sentences and assign to them an emoji, which is correct to describe their tone.
But machine learning is also applied to image and videos.
In those cases, we talk about computer vision.
An example of a computer vision application is image segmentation.
And that's what we'll play with a bit in the rest of the talk.
So in this case, we have an input image and we want to assign to different regions of
it different classes, depending on the content.
So here we have all this area, which is the background.
So we assign it the color black.
Here we have the vehicle.
So we color the motorcycle in a different way.
And we color the motorcyclist in a different way still.
What's nice nowadays is that it has become easier to at least apply machine learning
models if we program Python, because there are frameworks like PyTorch or TensorFlow
or scikit-learn that allow to run machine learning models easily.
So for instance, if we wanted to solve the image segmentation task that we just have
seen using PyTorch, we could do the following.
We could load a pre-trained model.
Here we trust the model provider to have trained correctly the model so it's both fair and
accurate.
And then we can essentially use this model a bit like a Python function on some input
image and get in output some model prediction, which is essentially this colored mask here.
This is very nice.
However, if we want to make the models useful for other users or make the models usable
for other computer applications, we need some other elements that are not provided by, for
instance, PyTorch or TensorFlow.
We need often to construct a front-end, so some kind of interface so that people can,
for instance, upload an image and then invoke the model by pressing a button and getting
results like in this example here.
For, well, not only front-end, we also need a back-end so that another application can
call the back-end and by sending an image and then getting a result.
This typically would be done, for instance, with a CUR URL call like this that references
the back-end endpoint.
So having a front-end and a back-end is really useful to make machine learning working in
a way for users and applications.
The problem is that you may need to master several technologies in order to build both.
And so wouldn't it be nice to build both the front-end and the back-end using pure Python
and hopefully without writing a lot of code?
So this can be done.
So I will propose a simple solution.
I will show it here that uses Python and Docker.
So Python is used here to build the front-end by employing the Streamlit library and instead
the back-end can be built using the FastAPI library.
Docker and in particular Docker Compose is used to make the front-end and back-end work
together and also can facilitate the deployment.
Let's talk a bit about the libraries that constitute the building blocks for the solution.
So one, as I said, is Streamlit and this is their website.
As they say here, they want to make it easy to build beautiful web applications, use the
machine learning and data science.
And I agree that this library can be very helpful to build simple UIs without writing
a lot of code.
You don't need to be an expert at JavaScript.
You don't need to know HTML to build these user interfaces.
The libraries, the Streamlit is pretty intuitive to use.
You essentially just write one line of code and this can translate into, this is translated
by the library into a widget in your user interface.
The project has become pretty popular.
It has 10,000 stars on GitHub and if you want to compare it with other frameworks like Dash
or Shiny, which is popular among our users, you can check this webpage on plotly.com.
Also let's talk about FastAPI.
They want to be high performance, easy to learn, fast to code and ready for production.
And indeed I found FastAPI to be capable of building APIs with documentation without writing
a lot of code.
FastAPI is especially easy to use if you know already Flask.
So anyway, I would agree that it's quite easy to learn.
Also because it has an extensive documentation and the lead developer, Sebastian Ramirez,
has recorded a lot of videos about how to use the library.
The project has become pretty popular.
It has 20,000 stars on GitHub and you can compare it with other popular frameworks like
Flask or Django by visiting this webpage.
So let's look more in detail inside our solution.
This is on GitHub.
Very happy to respond to issues if there are any and the code may have bugs.
So this is also open for pull requests.
The project is described on this blog post.
The architecture of the project is represented here.
We have two containers.
One takes responsibility for running the front end and that's powered by the Streamweek library.
This serves a user interface to users with descriptions and buttons and so on.
The front end also is capable of firing a request to the back end using the request
library.
And the back end runs using FastAPI and the core machine learning task, as we just said,
is done by PyTorch code.
So let's have a little walkthrough really quickly of the code.
The code as it is on GitHub is here.
So you have a Rigny file that explains a bit how to run the web application and also how
to deploy on Heroku and how to debug it.
The architecture is formalized in code in this Docker compose.yaml file.
As I said, we have two services, one for the back end, which is in the same Docker network
as the front end, the Streamweek container.
We also expose ports so that both the front end and the back end are reachable from the
outside.
So we can peek into the Python code of the back end.
So as we said, there is PyTorch code to run the machine learning model on a given image
and give an output result, the colored map.
So I won't go too much into detail because this is really taken from the PyTorch Hub
guide.
We essentially take the pre-trained model from the PyTorch Hub and then we have a function
which takes this model and runs it over a binary image.
There's also some pre-processing involved.
This is where we invoke the model.
We call the model to get the output predictions that are also given in output in the end by
the function.
So this PyTorch code is used inside the back end, as we said.
So here we have a fast API.
We indeed create a fast API object with a title for this is used in the app documentation
and also the same is true for the description.
And then the main part is this, where we declare an endpoint that the front end or another
application can call by passing an input and image.
This piece of code runs the model here and then returns to the client the machine learning
model result.
Let's have a look at the front end.
So the front end code is here and it uses Streamlit and the request library.
Requests are used to send the input given by the user to the fast API back end in this
processing function here.
And instead the construction of the UI layout is very simply done by Streamlit here.
So with this instruction we create a title for our web application, we will see this
in a second.
We write to the web page some description and also we create widgets so that users
can upload an image which will be stored in this variable.
This input image will be then kind of passed to the back end by invoking the process function
that we have seen above here.
And yeah, the call to the back end is triggered by the pressing of this button here.
Finally, the output result is shown to the user with this final Streamlit call.
So that's pretty much it.
If we want to run the application, we would just need to use Docker compose.
So let's do our Docker compose up.
This activates the fast API back end and the Streamlit front end containers.
And yeah, so let's have a look.
We can visit the front end at this address here and we can check that everything works.
Indeed, you can see the title here, the description of the application, different widgets that
we have created using Streamlit.
Okay, yeah, this is made with Streamlit indeed.
We have to wait a bit for the back end to process the image, but in the end we get the
result.
The back end documentation is now visible at this address.
So yeah, everything seems to be working.
In case we want to deploy the application on the web, we can use a tool like Heroku.
As far as I know, we need an add-on doc hero to run the application.
It takes about 10 minutes to deploy using the instruction that you find on the GitHub
repository.
And at the end of the process, you have a web application which is public on the web
and is accessible at this address for the front end.
And here we can visit the back end.
So that's pretty much it for the code walkthrough.
I hope that was enjoyable.
Thanks very much for attending the talk and I'm happy to take questions.