Hello, thank you for having the English track which I can present because my Spanish, if
you have spoken to me before, then you know it's not good. Hopefully next year I can give
a talk in Spanish maybe. Anyway, thank you so much for coming as well to listen to this
talk instead of other amazing talk. First of all, this is the slides and my Twitter handle
and stuff. I love people tweet about me, so please. If you love tweeting things, we are
a perfect match so you can tweet about me. So, yeah. So for those of you here, so do
you come here because you have been to a sprint, you know what is a sprint or you have no idea,
you just come here just to see what I'm going to talk about. So who have attended the sprint?
So, oh, there's a few of you. So you know what a sprint is, which is great. But before
I dive into the talk, I would like to introduce you to a different type of sprint. So, oh,
the picture is not loading. So, okay. I would basically, I don't know why the picture is
not loading, but maybe because it needs to be on. Anyway, this one actually you can find
the picture on my Twitter. So I was holding an ice cream on the street of Granada. So
I was having a Granada ice cream in Granada. So it's actually a joke that I sometimes,
you know, during a conference, I would, you know, type in the channel saying I'm going
for an ice cream sprint who's coming with me and like sometimes people come with me,
they thought it's a sprint at the conference. So they were like, oh, I've heard good things
about the sprint and join me and they end up eating an ice cream. So that's what I sometimes
do. So I'm checked. Oh, this is loading. Good. Okay. So hello, I'm checked. And I work in
a lot of open source project. I love open source project. I think open source project
are important. And also I, yeah, so I also organize a lot of conference. I also organize
something called pattern sprints in the past. It's not coming back after the pandemic yet
because I was too busy. But anyway, so this is all the conference that I've been involved
in the past. Also I stream a little bit on Twitch during the pandemic because I was having
too much time at hand. So that's what I did. So what is the sprint that we got to talk
about now? It's not the sport. For those of you who are very athletic and love running,
so that's not that type of sprint. I actually have been to a lot of sprints, but I don't
actually understand why it's called a sprint. And what does it mean? So I, you know, I have
to give a talk, right? So I have to look it up. I have to find it on the internet. And
then, so in the internet actually says that in, you know, software development, sometimes,
you know, we have this development cycle and then you will have these kind of sprints.
That means that for a small team of member, they have to, you know, they may have a lot
of problem to solve or they have a lot of new features need to add. So they would, you
know, put that go into small task and then try to finish it within a set amount of time.
So that's the sprint. It's software development. So basically just sit together and finish
some small tasks. That's basically what a sprint means in software development. But
when we go to a conference, we are not actually developing a software. Nobody pay, well, nobody
got to pay you, you know, give you money in the conference. So you, you know, you don't
go to the conference to work, well, except maybe me, but you don't, you don't, you know,
you don't go to a conference, you know, to expect to be developing some software and
get paid, right? So what does it mean about a sprint in a conference? So in the sprint
in the conference, so I think some of you already know, especially for those of you
who has been to a sprint, that basically it's just fixing some bugs and writing some, you
know, a test and then closing some issues. Isn't it? Like we just, you know, go to find
an open source project and then go to the GitHub and then do what, you know, you think
a contribution would be. And it's just to find issues and try to make a PR, you know,
make it do be accepted. And then everybody's happy. But I would like to say that a sprint
contribution is just, is not limited to just code contribution. A lot of time people mistaken
and thought that open source contribution need to be technical, need to be some code
or some tests. Some people may think, oh yeah, documentation. Yes. But that's, you know,
that's some people like, that's people with experience with things that documentation
is also important. Most people just think that I need to write some code to contribute
to a project, which I'm going to tell you today. That's not true. This is, I was just
inspired by the keynote just before because she was talking about the conversational AI
and things like that. I would like to introduce you to this. This is a Mozilla common voice
project. I have contributed to it before, but I didn't write any code. I just go and
speak my mother tongue because at that time I found this project by a tweet, someone saying
that, you know, oh, they need a Cantonese speaker to contribute to this database and
to, you know, also listen to verify whether some recordings are correct and things like
that. So, when I was at the keynote, I was, you know, trying to understand it, I think,
oh, yes, because in a lot of machine learning and things like that, it's written or the
database that they use would be in more popular language, English, or, you know, now they're,
like, I think that by the example that was shown in the keynote, the Spanish model was
quite good as well. But if you speak any other language or maybe, you know, you know, someone
who speak any other language that is less spoken, then that may be something you can
contribute to open source. It's not code. It's just what you can do to help the community.
This is again a picture that's missing. I forgot that the picture won't work if I use
another computer. But anyway, this picture, again, you can find it on Twitter. So this
is a picture that I was talking in PyCon Portugal, actually, sorry, it's JungleCon Europe in
Portugal last week. So this is at the end of the conference. I took a picture at the
auditorium where, during the closing, when there are lots of volunteers that come on
stage and then, you know, everybody claps because we thank them because they contribute
to the community. They didn't, like, well, maybe they also can, you know, they're also
technical, maybe they can code or maybe they work as a software developer, but they contribute
to the community by other things, by organizing things, by, you know, and organize the coffee
break, you know, code won't give you coffee break and the yummy pastry that you just had,
right? So someone needs to organize that. Someone needs to make that happen. And there's also
contribution to organize events to do stuff that's not code-based for the community. But
then go back to the sprints, like, why we do the sprints? Why we just, like, not, you
know, do what we want for the community? Well, because the sprint is actually something
that would really help you in your journey in the community, I would say, because there
are a few benefits that I can think of that I think that would really, you would really
enjoy and benefit from the sprint. For example, you can make new friends. Some example, including,
you know, if you go to a sprint at the conference, you will meet some project maintainers that
you may have used the package or the library for your work for a long time, but you have
never met the maintainers. In my example, when I was started working as a data scientist,
I used pandas a lot, right? So I hope all of you have heard about pandas, at least. So
it's a library for managing data, so it's very popular. And by going to a sprint, I
matched the maintainer of pandas for the first time, and they are really nice people. I
wasn't expecting that because at that time I was not that, you know, I was new to the
community. I don't understand too much how it works. I just think that all these people
must be genius that they create this stuff for us to use for free. But when I meet them,
they are actually real people. They are just like you and me, but they may have created
something or working on something that is very popular. I do have a lot of respect for
them, but they are also very nice. And just like they would talk to you, they would, you
know, so you thought they are, oh my God, like these people, maybe they are too good
for me to talk to. No, they would talk to you. It's very nice that you become their
friends. And then you can learn about a new package. There are things that you may have
not never heard of. You may, it's maybe something that is outside of your work domain that you
may never, ever know what it's going to do. If you go to a sprint, then usually at the
beginning of the sprint, people will come and explain what the project they are leading.
So some of the fun ones are like, for example, I learned about a library called Pi Game Zero
that actually is about making games or pipe them. Something that I would never think about
I would know and pipe and could do at that time. And so I would know about a new project
and then a new package that you have never heard of. And if it's not for the sprint,
I would never get a chance to know what it is and look at the code and try it out myself.
Also to get inspired, a lot of times, you know, you keep working for your work or something,
your code, you use the package that you use every day, you thought you know it inside
out, you thought you are a very advanced user. But at the sprint, when you actually look
at the source code of the project, then you would actually understand that there may be
another better way of doing it. That you have never thought of if you are just doing your
day-to-day work. So which is very good. And something that, you know, I think it's an
experience that you can't really get a lot when you are just working with the same group
of people in your company and things like that. The last thing is to collaborate. A
lot of times, I have, I see people that they are maybe working on similar libraries. They
would actually cross-check how do you do this? Or maybe there are some upstream dependencies
that, you know, for example, in Python US, we have sprints. And then I was working with
a maintainer of the hypothesis. So, you know, we were testing our things and then we found
out, oh, there is something that maybe the newer version of Python, C Python, that gives
us a strange error or something like that. So there is a chance because the C Python
developers are sitting in the next room, just next door. You can go there and hello, I have
this problem. And talk to them. So not just that, but other libraries like PyTest. We
also try to test a lot of things with PyTest. And sometimes if we have a question, we can
just ask the people working on PyTest. So it's very easy to collaborate. Instead of
you may have to open an issue, well, you can still open an issue during the sprints.
But on top of that, you know, there is something that you may be lost in the communication,
in the typing. You can just talk to the real person who may take care of that issue for
you. So that's really good. So this is, again, the picture of the ice cream because I want
to say that with the ice cream sprints, you can also make friends. Maybe exchange ideas,
but maybe not sit down and code. So that's the only difference. So you do learn a lot
in the sprint, which is something that I am advocating for, that for people, because
I've seen a lot of times during the conference. You know, some conference they will have sprint
date as their tradition. But I have met some participant that they would just disappear
during the sprint date. It's fine, but I would recommend if you have never tried, maybe think
about that. I will tell you my personal experience. Again, I was sprinting on hypothesis. So who
have used hypothesis before and know what it is? So one, two, a few. Okay, good. So hypothesis
is a testing library that is doing property-based testing. So I won't dive into too much detail,
but it's just a testing library. If you want to know more, you can watch my previous talks
in other conferences. So I was working on hypothesis. I have used hypothesis before,
a little bit. But then by going to the sprint, I learned something new, because who knows
that there is a ghost writer in hypothesis? None. Yeah, so I wasn't one of you. I didn't
heard about ghost writer before, but because I was at the sprints, I was contributing to
a hypothesis. And then I was tackling this issue with ghost writer. Then I was scratching
my head. Wait a second. What is a ghost writer? So I read the documentation of ghost writer.
I understand what it's trying to achieve. Look at the code base and try to solve the
problem that that issue was describing. So by going to the sprints, by contribution,
you learn something new that you may overlook, because you have never used it before and
never heard of it before. So that's the benefit of doing that. There's also other great ideas
can come from the sprints. A lot of times, you know, we have a lot of amazing projects
that people are doing during the sprint. So this is actually something that all of you
can contribute, because this is the project of translating the Python documentation into
Spanish. So I think the first time I heard about this effort was a few years ago, I think,
in maybe Euro Python. But I think it started in Python US years ago. So I think it's still
ongoing because you can see that it's now Python 3.10.7, but Python 3.11 is coming out
and there will be new features and new things that need to be translated. So next time,
you know, maybe consider, you know, maybe talk to someone who is more experienced in
this effort and then if you go to a sprints, you can maybe lead the effort to start translating
some new things about the C Python documentation. So by doing that, actually, you are contributing
also to C Python, going back to the point that not all contribution are code contribution.
It's also a contribution, so highly recommend that. So to sum up, I think, is like everything
just go back to the community. So missing picture again. So this picture, actually, you
don't have to look at it online, you can just go downstairs, back to the main hall. Next
to the registration, there was a bot. So there was a bot yesterday, I took a picture yesterday,
so it asked what does Python mean to you? And people write stuff there, right? So I
try to understand what people are written down. So I saw one person with the green pen
written down community. Which is community. So what Python means to you is the community.
And I totally agree on that. Because for me, a lot of people ask me, why do you prefer
Python? It's a very good programming language. I would answer that. I am not technical enough
to judge different languages because I can write Python, I learn a little bit of maybe
JavaScript and things, but I don't know enough to judge what programming language is better
than the other. Or maybe there's no good answer to that because they may be for different
tasks. But I can proudly tell people that the Python community could probably be the
best. That's why I am in this zone. I am in the Python community. So community is a very
important part of Python, I would say. So without the community, there will be no sprints.
Just like I said before, things doesn't just happen. Just like the coffee break, just like
the keynote, just like anything, the room that you are sitting in right now. Without the
community, without people organizing it, there will be no sprints. Nothing will happen. There
will be no conference and no sprints. But without the sprints, there will be less contributions.
People are less aware that they can actually do something for the community. They can translate
the documentation, they can, you know, if you can, you can also work on a code if you
want to. Or you can, you know, try some new libraries and find out some issues and report
it back. Without the sprints, there may still be contributions, but there will be much less.
Because you are refined in your zone of your work. Maybe a few, you know, pet projects
and hobby projects, but it's quite limited. And then without the contributions, there's
no community. Because, again, you know, without the contribution, without people putting effort
in, we won't be gathering here. The Python community won't be the same. So this is the
picture. Again, look up on my Twitter. Actually, don't look it up on my Twitter. Look it up
on the EuroSciPy Twitter. This is probably the top tweet from EuroSciPy. So EuroSciPy
happened at the end of August. So just two months ago now. Or actually, like last, yeah,
it's like end of August. So it was EuroSciPy. And then it's a five-day conference, right?
Very intense, you know. If you have been to a conference, you know, conference is, you
know, you socialize with people when you work, you know, have to use your brain because you
go to workshops and talks and then you socialize again at the end and then maybe go out late.
But at the end of EuroSciPy, there's a day of sprint. And this is the, supposedly, like
if it doesn't mess up, the picture was taken during the sprint. And it was a room full
of people. I was very impressed because I told you, I've met people that sometimes
they left after the conference. They may be too tired or they have other things at home
they have to take care of, they have to go back early or they would rather check out the
city. But at EuroSciPy, it was the first, actually, it was the first time they organized
in Basel. So it's a new city for a lot of people. People decided to not go around but
stay in the room, actually two rooms but they are both full, around 70 people. Compared
to a conference, there's around 200 people that stay in the room to contribute to the
open source project. I was very impressed and I hope that may be the case for a lot of different
conferences as well. So I've told you a lot about why sprint is good, why contributing
is good. But sometimes we have challenges. So who know about HectorvaFest, which is happening
now? Yes, some of you. So every year there's this event called HectorvaFest. The idea is
to encourage people to contribute to open source project. I haven't been actively participated
for a few years but in the past when I was actively participating, they would give free
t-shirts for people who signed up and contribute to free pool requests, to free contribution,
you have a free t-shirt. The idea is really good but technically it created some problem
because they create a lot of noise, a lot of people. I can't tell you what their intention
is but I have been told by some maintainers that there are some pool requests that are
not a very effective pool request because they may fix some minor typos or just some
even, for example today I saw a tweet, one maintainer was saying someone just go to the
Q&A page and add question and answer in front of the question and answers, which is not
necessary but people do make that kind of pool request, try to finish the quest to get
the free t-shirt. So it's a lot of maintainers nowadays, they doubt about this effort, they
doubt about whether this is a healthy thing to encourage people to contribute like that.
I would say that yes, Hector Buffett's do have a fault, some people may not truly understand
the idea of contributing and they just want to get the t-shirt but I think by organizing
a sprinch those things can be minimized because in a sprinch people sit together in the room,
you can have an introductory talk or something to explain to people what's the idea of a
contribution and how they can contribute and also there will be better guidance because
the maintainer will be there sitting with them and guide them through some pool requests
or issues that is suited for their ability so they don't have to be struggling in finding
something that they can do so they end up doing something that is not very helpful for
the project. So that's why I think that if you ask me how to improve Hector Buffett's,
I would say we can't just run Hector Buffett's without the support with the sprints that
we actually put an effort to guide people to contribute and also some maintainer may
say that running a sprinch, guiding people to solve the problem is more difficult than
solving the problem themselves but why do they do that? Same question may happen in your
company that why do you teach your junior developers or interns to do stuff? It's faster
to do it yourself. If you stay up, maybe stay later at work one day you can finish all of
them. Why spend another extra day or two to teach them, to guide them, to make them grow?
The problem is we need to make them grow. We need to have people. One day we would all
want to be retired and if young people or new people doesn't come in and get the help
that they need, then we may not have good developers or it will only be the developers
who are just like in the environment that they have advantage of. That's why if we want
a community with more diversity and inclusion, we should also put in more efforts to support
people who are maybe less confident because they see themselves as minority and you need
to give them more encouragement and more support. That's why if you are a maintainer or if
you are a more senior developer, try to help others, try to be kind and help younger or
maybe newer people in the community to grow, to learn. I think that's a D.N. of my talk.
I would like to ask this question and leave this to you. Do we want the spring at PyCon
Spain next year? If your answer is yes, I would love to see that. Talk to the organizers
and tell them that you would love to join us. You would love to be sitting with amazing
people next year and maybe it will happen. That's it for me. Thank you.