Welcome Francesco and Israel.
We talk the migration without downtime.
So hello.
I'm Francesco.
I work for Travel Perk and is one of my colleagues.
We both work as software engineers.
And let's deep dive in the topic.
So what we do, what our company does,
is basically provide a solution to buy, to book,
and manage the business travel as a whole thing.
So whatever is related from the booking to the management
and to the post booking and everything
is can be done in the platform.
So what we offer to be different than others
is that we have a huge inventory.
We have unified payment and invoicing system.
We also offer many options to upload the users in the platform
and sync them in real time.
Something like bamboo HR, if you know it.
Something like SQL Scheme is another protocol
that we use to sync users.
But those are a little bit technical.
Also from a business point of view,
we offer the possibility to define different policies
and different approval processes.
Because in some companies, there is
the need to control what the employees are booking.
Also reporting, cost management, and carbon
offsetting, which is a huge topic for us right now.
So what we offer is the possibility
to contribute in being more green, let's say.
Also, we have different pricing levels.
So any company can decide what they need for their business.
And we have an amazing 24-7 customer service.
If I can add something, probably,
since you came here to the conference,
are you out in a company with a lot of people?
You can see the pain that it can be sometimes
for having one central person, like having
to manage all the travel for everyone,
because you need to ask for all the data, the passport,
whatever, everyone has to send the final confirmation
in advance with the codes to everyone.
So one thing that we do in the platform,
which has to do from the business and power,
the travelers to book the travel themselves within a policy.
So if you are an employee in the company,
instead of having to contact the office manager or the travel
manager of the company, you can book your own travel
using the payment methods of the company that
give you a bank transfer or Sepadabit.
So it's much easier for everyone in the company
instead of having to have one central point, which
is a lot when the company speaks.
So for me, it's one of the big value proposals for companies.
So OK, what we are talking today is
about doing modifications and changes to the database
without causing a disruption of the service.
Because as you see, as you saw before, we are providing the solution
as a service online.
So what we want to avoid is for our clients
to experience like disruption in their service
once we update the database.
But we are going a little bit down now for some basics.
And we will talk about models in general.
We will talk about migration.
And then we'll explain the strategy
we are using to avoid the actual downtime.
So what are migrations?
First, let's talk about the models.
It's a funny one.
So the models are basically what Django provides us
to model the schema in the database.
So we have in the code the representation
that we want to give to the tables.
Let's say you can define the same constraints
and the same options that you can define at the database level
but in Python, let's say.
So what you see there is like a basic example of a model
that can have two fields.
One is question text.
One is pub date.
And how it is mapped into the SQL DDL.
Which is you can see that in the model, we have two fields.
And in the table, we have three.
Because Django by default provides the ID as an auto increment.
But let's go to the migrations now.
So what is a migration?
Migration is what Django provides us to actually apply
modifications to the database.
So what we want, for example, is
adding a field, deleting a field, adding a default value
for a column to the database.
Whatever is impacting the schema level, the changes
that we do at the model is done via migration with Django.
So this is just a simple representation of what happens.
So when we want to change the model A to A1, what Django does
is what we need to do is actually create the migration.
It's done by this command called make migration.
And it generates basically a meta language that
contains a SQL that is actually applied when we go to production
to actually modify the table.
And in the migration file, you can review the changes
if you want to take a look to everything.
So let's say it's split into phases.
First, we create the first Django creates this migration
file called migration file.
And then when going in production,
you need to actually apply the migration.
This is an example.
As you see, so all the migrations extend
from migrations.migration, which is the Django class for it.
The dependencies are explaining what
are the previous migrations that need to be run
before running this one.
And the operation is what actually
was going on with the migration.
In this case, there is a model tree
that gets deleted so the table gets eliminated.
And the migration is adding the rating
field to the author model.
There is an integer.
So that's roughly this simple migration what it's doing.
This is a graph that explains the flow that
happened with the migration.
So as you can see, it kind of looks
similar like the Gitflow.
Because what it's saying is starting
for the migration 1A to B3C, there is a branching.
Because the 4D one and the 4D are actually
depending only on the 3C.
So they can go in parallel.
And then once everything gets merged,
let's say after a few other migrations,
everything goes linear again.
And the representation that you see on the right
after the command show migration is basically
show migration is the command that shows all the migrations
that are applied to the current database level.
So in that case, when you run show migration,
if you see what's shown there, so 01 initial 02 auto,
it means that the one with the X has been applied already
on the database.
The second one is not yet applied.
So you need to run a specific command to do it, as I said
before.
Let's go to the next.
This is just a repetition.
Sorry.
This is just to wrap up a little bit what I said before.
So the workflow that happens when we
need to execute a migration, it's just
running the command that is listed there,
that is the migrate command.
And the running migration report is basically
what's going on in production.
If you see the logs, you will see this,
because every migration that gets applied
is logged with an OK or KO in case it's not going well.
So this is just a recap of the commands that
can be run to end of migration.
The migrate, as I said before, is the way we have to actually
apply the migrations in the database.
Make migration is to create the migration file from the change
to the model that we're doing.
So when we change the model, we always
need to run mic migration to generate the migration file,
so the same change can be applied at the database level.
Because otherwise, there is the possibility
that the model and the database are not aligned,
and this can be quite a big problem.
The SQL migrate is a tool that you
can use to actually inspect the SQL that is generated
from a migration file.
So it's just if you want to be more on control of what's
going on, you can run this command
and you can see what is actually happening at the database
level.
And the show migration, as we showed before,
is just to see which migration has been applied already
and which are not yet.
So now I leave the word to Isra.
OK.
So if you got a bit confused by all what we said,
it was just an introduction.
The purpose of the talk was not to talk about how migrations
work, but to avoid downtime.
It was just a bit of context, so you understand everything.
So don't worry.
Now I'm going to talk, know that we are introduced models
and migrations.
I'm going to talk a bit about the main purpose of the talk,
which is downtime when you're applying migrations
and why they happen and how can we try to avoid them.
OK.
So OK.
What we want to say is why do they happen?
And there are two reasons why they can happen.
The first one is that usually when you're running an application
that you don't want to have downtime,
you need to deploy a new version of the app
while the previous version is running.
So you don't stop the previous version, then apply the migration,
apply the change the database, and start the new one.
Because there can be even a few seconds.
These seconds can mean a lot in certain systems,
so you don't want that.
So what you do, I think I have a graph here.
Yeah.
You deploy the new version of the app
while the previous version is running.
And then this creates an issue.
Why?
Because you can have two versions of the app, the old one,
and the new one with the new models in Python
running at the same time.
But you cannot have two schemas of the database.
I don't know.
Perhaps there are some databases that allow that.
But you cannot have two schemas.
When you run the migration, you apply a change to the schema,
and then it's a different one.
Perhaps you have a field that was nullable before,
and no, it's not nullable.
So it cannot run with both versions at the same time.
OK.
Then you can see the two versions.
At some point, there are two of them running.
But the database schema changes when
you apply the migration.
That is a separate command.
So what happens if you are, for example, deleting a more?
Are you?
Yeah.
OK.
You did it on purpose.
What happens if you are deleting a model, for example,
and that model was in use by the application?
What happens if you change a field or delete a field?
And this field, of course, it was being used.
It cannot be OK.
Or you change attributes.
Like, for example, you make a field not nullable.
And then every time the old app tries
to create that model or change something,
and this is nullable, then OK, then it's going to fail.
OK.
Then in order to avoid that, basically a rule of thumb
is that to have backwards compatibility every time
you make a change, you need to make the new schema compatible
with the old application.
And we will see, I'm trying to introduce the main reasons.
It can have downtime.
And later, under the rules of thumb,
later we will see some examples of the typical operations
that we do.
How can we avoid that?
OK.
This is the main thing to consider.
Whenever you are running this, take this into account.
The new version has to be compatible with the old app.
OK.
And then the second reason, the second main reason
that you can have downtime is the locks in the database.
Basically, whenever you have a data
structure that you need to perform certain operations,
in order to have certain guarantees of the reliability
of the data, that different operations see the same data,
et cetera, et cetera, there are mechanisms called locks
that prevent multiple operations that are not
compatible among them to have these guarantees
run simultaneously.
Because if they run simultaneously,
you can have inconsistent data.
If you are, I don't know, deleting a file at the same time
updating, it doesn't make sense.
Then it doesn't work.
So in order to do that, well, in this case, in our company,
we use Postgres.
I guess that in MySQL, there can be similar things.
But the data system implement mechanism called locks,
where they basically, when there are two operations,
depending on the kind of exclusivity
that they need in the operations, they say, OK,
I lock this, for example, this row or this table,
and nothing can write there, for example.
And until I finish this transaction,
the next operation cannot do anything.
This way, you stop there.
There are my get-on there.
And you know that you are not breaking anything in the data.
Imagine it's a bank.
And you do multiple, imagine you do double transactions
or stuff like that.
So you want to be able to lock stuff.
So even things could happen concurrently.
You don't do that in order to avoid mistakes.
I said a lot of things.
But then the problem with this is that almost always,
whenever there's a migration and you
have an alter table statement, for example, adding a field
or changing something, I think that almost all
alter table statements, which are the ones like use migrations,
acquire a kind of lock that is called access,
I think it's called access exclusive,
on the table that is being modified.
What does this mean?
This means that, basically, it stops when it's running.
No other operation, no other transaction
can run on the same table.
Then what happens?
If you have an alter table that takes a long time,
then even if it's just reading, and really,
it was not important because it could just,
I don't know, adding a field.
OK, you're adding a field.
And then you are reading from other fields.
It's not important.
But the table is locked.
So nothing can read from that table.
And then if the transaction, the alter table,
takes a long time for any reason, then,
and if this long time is obviously subjective,
depending on the SLI of your application.
If your application needs to return,
I don't know, your Google, and you
need to return in less than, I don't know, 100 milliseconds,
five seconds can be a lot.
Some other companies, OK, you can have four more downtime.
It's OK.
But if this is longer, and the more data you have,
usually, if there are read writes of table and stuff
like that, the longer the alter table takes,
because sometimes they have to rewrite the entire table,
and it takes a long time.
Then you need to control for this.
And you need to be aware of the alter table locking the tables
even for this and for everything.
OK, here you have a representation,
OK, where there are some transactions.
In data-based operations, there are always transactions.
So there can be some transaction.
At some point, we introduced the fifth transaction,
which is the migration, where we are doing the migrate command
that we saw before.
And then there was this sixth transaction
that could have run, perhaps, in that table.
But the fifth one was locking the table.
So perhaps the sixth one was super fast.
But since the previous one started earlier,
then now it cannot work.
And it can take, I don't know, one minute,
even if it was fast, because it arrived too late,
OK, because the table is locked.
You see.
OK, an important thing to highlight here
is something that is not very well known,
is that this is a complex thing.
And the locks on the tables, what at least Postgres does,
it has a first in, first out.
It has a queue of the locks to acquire.
So in this case, I'm going to put all these things.
OK, so it's easy to see.
You have, for example, one long running query,
for example, a select or account on a table, a very big one.
And then imagine it takes, I don't know, 30 seconds to run.
And then while it's running, imagine on the second one,
you apply the migration.
I say, OK, it needs to alter that table.
But that other select query is running.
Then when you do the alter table, what Postgres does,
since the select is running and the alter table cannot acquire
the lock on that table, because there's another transaction,
it waits for the lock.
But then if another operation comes,
the next operation cannot either go and do any operations
on the table, because there was a long running one.
The third one is compatible with the first one,
but the second one is in the middle.
I don't know why it's like that, but I guess
that is because otherwise, imagine that then, OK,
we say, OK, the first one is compatible with the third one,
then we let the third one pass.
But then the other table, in some scenarios,
can perhaps, if there are a lot of transactions,
perhaps it never runs.
So it has a queue.
So it says, before, if this operation has not finished yet,
the next one cannot go.
So you have a very busy table, where there are a lot of some
cases where the transaction that run very long,
even if the alter table is short in time,
the long running query is the one that is going to make
the rest of the transactions later queue up,
and then cost downtime.
And this has happened to us a lot.
And you say, why is this happening?
Because we had some query that was like four, five seconds,
and it was locked.
So yeah, that's what I said.
OK, then, Russell Thunford is to try to avoid this.
First, the SQL migrate command that Francesco
was talking about.
Every time you are running a migration,
check the SQL is being run.
So this way, you can check documentation
and try to understand what kind of blocks are acquired
and try to prevent bad things happening,
especially if they are big tables or they
are big or busy tables.
Because the big tables usually takes more time.
Then the second thing is there are some operations
that need to rewrite the whole table.
It was the case, I will talk later,
of Postgres when you were applying a non-nulable default,
it had to rewrite the whole table.
So it's a big one.
And you have the alter during a transaction,
then you say, OK, add this default by default.
The value has to be three, or zero,
in this new field that I add.
But before, it had to rewrite the whole table,
and it took a long time.
It's millions of records, and it locks for that time.
And it's terrible.
In some cases there, you can do alter tables
with less restrictive blocks, which is good then,
because then you have less chances of everything blocking.
If the other restrictive blocks are unavoidable,
an important thing is that to run the locking things
separated from the rest.
For example, you have a migration.
Later, you have to do a data migration,
which is changing some data, run them
in different transactions.
Why?
Because you put them in the same transaction,
the lock is going to be held until the end of the transaction.
Even if the other table was fast,
or you can put the first one, the order doesn't matter,
but the locks are for transaction.
So then you separate them.
You separate them.
The stronger lock, the access-clusive lock,
we will have for a short time, and then you
have the long-running operation that
is compatible with all the rest.
And then for the last part, I think
we have this good, because we are on time.
I'm going to show some examples of typical operations
where you can have downtime and hope to avoid them.
This is the important thing, perhaps, for some people.
That said, probably you look for this topic online.
You will find other people talking about this
and telling them how to avoid this.
So probably better explain that we are explaining here.
So yeah, yeah.
For me, at least, we are not trying
to show you to have an exhaustive list of all
the possible cases.
Just to show you the typical cases,
then you look up online.
You will find documentation where you have every case,
and why, et cetera, et cetera.
OK.
I don't know if you can see this.
It's not very easy.
It's my fault.
I don't know how to do slides that work in these things.
Yeah.
Adding a normal field.
Adding a field is normally safe because at least now,
starting with Postgres 11, even if you
have a non-nullable default, it doesn't
need a full rewrite on the table.
Before, it had to do a full rewrite that took a really long
time to run.
So why is this?
Because I don't know if you know,
but Django keeps the default in the code, not in the database.
So when you added a non-nullable field with a default,
it had to first add the column with the default value,
and then drop the default.
And this adding the column with the default value
was what was making rewrite the whole table.
So the important thing is this second thing is already solved.
Otherwise, you had to resort to nasty tricks.
You can find somewhere else.
And important thing to avoid, the first problem
that I talked about, which was the two versions of the same
app running at the same time, is that the new field has
to have null equal true.
Why?
Because the old version of the app
will try to write in that model and say, OK, put this data.
And obviously, there's a field that is missing,
and then it will fail.
So OK, this file constraint, this field cannot be null,
and you are making it null.
OK, it's going to fail.
So nullable, you can make another migration later
to make it nullable.
But nullable and the other issue, it's OK.
Forget about it.
Adding fields, foreign keys, when you have foreign keys,
it needs to acquire a specific kind of lock in the table
that you were adding the key and the other table,
because it needs to check that you know how foreign keys work.
The version in the first, the number in the first table
has too much, and only in the second table.
Otherwise, there's an inconsistency.
That's the basic thing.
So if it's a new field and it was not referencing,
if it was not a normal field that you added a foreign key later,
usually it's empty.
So it doesn't have to check this constraint
on all the values.
So it's usually very fast.
So you don't need to do anything.
But if you need to turn up, imagine
you have a normal before an integer field,
and then you turn into a foreign key,
then you need to do a specific trick that we list there.
Basically, it's creating the foreign key,
but without validating it, and then later validating it
in a different transaction.
So you can run both things at the same time.
And as I put there, that is a fast operation.
But remember the issue with the long-running transaction.
If you're adding, might you have a table that has
some long-running transaction, and then you
add a foreign key to it, then the problem you will have
is that it will hold this lock, and there will be,
you cannot do updates on that table
until the long transaction ends, finishes running.
Five minutes, good.
Adding models is very, don't worry,
it's the same with the foreign key.
If there are long-running transactions
if you are adding foreign keys to a table,
otherwise it's a new model.
You are not really changing anything,
just adding a new model.
Renaming field, usually you should try to avoid that.
If the column name in the database is not important,
Django has a mechanism to say, OK, perhaps
you want to rename it just to make it more clear for other
people.
You can just say, OK, I changed the name of the field
in Python, but the database name is another one.
So you can do this.
But if you really want to change the column in the database,
then you have to do a lot of nasty things
that are right here.
You need to create another field.
If you don't want on time, you need to create another field,
update both, do some data migration
so you get all the old values into the both fields
at the same time, and then delete the old one.
Because otherwise, we have this issue
with adding fields that are, if they cannot be nulled,
then you have these kind of issues.
You cannot just change it directly,
because then it will try to write in the old one,
and then it won't work.
The previous version of the app.
So this is how you do it.
Changing attributes in a foreign key.
This is something that hit us hard sometimes,
at least in the past.
Django, every time you did any change at all
in a field containing a foreign key,
it was dropping the foreign key and recreating it again.
Of course, if this is a foreign key that references two big
tables, it needs to check the constraint in both tables
that are being referenced.
And as I said, to validate this foreign key constraint,
it takes a long time, and it was like blocking everything
there.
So this was a big issue.
It was improved a bit in Django 3.2, where they added,
where if you are changing some stuff in the field,
that doesn't really change the database.
Nothing is done, but for some other things,
like something that happened to us,
you had a field that was not nulled all before,
and you make it nullable, and it was still dropping the foreign
key and recreating it with the same issues as before.
You can see there, Django provides a way to say, OK,
the model changes are this, but don't do any operation.
For example, it's called Migrations Rule
SQL or Migrations Separate Database and State,
where you can see, where you can say, OK, the model changes
like this, but I'm telling you which SQL operations I want
to run in order to talk about Django running things on its own.
It's really nice.
Indexes.
Also, when you add indexes, what happens?
Postgres by default, when you're creating an index on a field,
OK, let's add index, because the data will be faster,
because we have this really big table, where, of course,
we need to run a query and search for things really fast.
Let's create the index.
Good, nice.
But when you create the index, it block writes on the table,
because the way it computes the index,
it needs, OK, you change the values of the table, of course,
something is going to be wrong with the index.
Then you need, instead of doing the default,
Django added an operation that it can be done in progress,
adding index concurrently that doesn't block updates,
basically.
And dropping should be fast, except in the case
of other online transactions.
OK, delete fields.
This is a very complicated thing.
I don't think I have a lot of time, like two minutes.
Basically, I wrote here the operations
that you need to do.
We did this multiple times.
It's very painful, because of the backwards compatibility.
If you cannot just delete it, because obviously,
the previous app will try to select those fields that
were existing in the previous app.
So you need to do all these things.
First, OK, it's nullable, so I don't write it anymore.
Don't use it in the code.
Then you delete the field in the model,
deploy a new version that is not using this field at all.
Why wait until?
This is fully deployed.
And then when you have the new code that
doesn't use this field at all anymore, then you delete it.
But you need to run the migration after you
deployed the new version that doesn't use the field,
is fully deployed.
Because otherwise, the previous version
will try to select it.
Because Django, when you query for a model,
it tries to get all the fields of the model by default.
So it will try to get the field that doesn't exist anymore.
So you need to delete it from the model, deploy,
and then run the migration.
And for deleting models, it's like similar thing
that the previous slide, you need to do more or less the same.
Like delete the usage.
Deploy the version.
The Python version doesn't use those fields anymore.
And then after you have done that, then run the migration.
You need to stop using those fields and those models
in the code before those models and those fields
are deleted from the database.
And that's it.
Some links that we use is very, of course,
the Postgres documentation that you
can check to understand more about logs.
And some posts that we found useful about some company
called Citus Data, where they explain how logs work
and how to avoid certain situations with logs
when you are doing changes in the schema changes
in the database.
And that's all.
Other companies you have seen, we are hiring, obviously.
You want to join or you are interested in business travel
for your company as well.
Talk to us.
Yeah, and that's it.
Thank you very much.
Have a good day.
Thank you.