I am going to try to tell you why, when you see it or discuss it or
whatever. Well, the different sections are what are feature flags, why, the
problem, the antecedent, face approach, how, improve the
approach, the properties, the difference between feature flags and blue
green or configuration managing, good principles and issues, risk or why don't
use feature flags. Don't expect hype. I'm going to provide a full set of reasons
for not using them but also they provide good, is a good tool for in many
circumstances. Okay, what are feature flags? That's for me it's the
definition of feature flag is a process that allows you to modify the
behavior of your system but or without deploying code or any don't time just on
the fly. At the end, it's an if in your code. You can say time, it's only that but
there are more, when you dig into the feature flags, there are more things
probably you need to know. That's what I want to tell you. For me, it's not only
don't time, it's about being able to monitorize the changes you do. The couple,
these changes in the code from the on the code and also keeping that changes or
keeping that ability, that tool totally out of your architecture or your system
being totally flexible. Yeah, why or what do you expect to get if you use
feature flag? Well, probably you are going to find or you are going to improve
your continuous delivery.
Probably you will be able to study or you should be able to study or prevent
any performance issues in the new release before that they happen. You should
be able to do rollbacks or avoid rollbacks because you prevent the issues
before the release but just in case you will be able to do it. People love
microservices. Some people when we talk about feature flags say don't use
microservices with feature flags because it's well you know many times using
microservices, following the tracking the what time running exactly is hard.
So if you have more logical path as feature flag does, it's
harder but it's a way to use microservices. You can use them with
feature flag too. Many people say thanks to feature flags you can decrease the
code lead time. Since the beginning you start to code a feature until the moment
you release that feature. Decrease the failure rate, being able to do AB
deploys. So you can study you have two different features at the same time and
you can study two different sets of uses and how they do what they do.
Validation of the code can be improved. I told about the resized
decreases and one of the most important thing for the people is you can modify
the behavior of your system but no disruptions. Well there are four types of
feature flags. It's those related to the release. Imagine you have a
migration.
When people talk about migration with no downtime, people used to say okay put the
logic of the migration but don't run the migration or later put the logic
related to the new structure and so on. Well feature flags allows you to deploy a
code but not active that code until the moment you active that feature flag. I
told about the AB deploys, being able to experiment different
features with different sets of uses. Operational, that kind of feature
flags are related to allowing to capture more resources or to create more
cues without... it's like okay don't disturb the DevOps or system administrator.
Create changing the behavior of the system to prepare you for for different
moments with spikes of users or whatever and the last one is related to
permissions. Different users, different groups, imagine this
this place, the PyCon. There are people who is part of the organization, people
who is visiting so all us, sorry, we can go into Eventbrite. Some of us just
we just can take our ticket or the user they can check if the
ticket is related to the PyCon or not. Different information is shown.
Okay that kind of thing. One of the issues about feature flags is
as I say every time you create a feature flag you split your logic in
two different ways. More you do that, either to follow the structure or the
path the code is running. So when you create a feature flag, when you design a
feature flag, you should take into account that feature flag should die
eventually. You will create, you will deploy the feature flag into production,
you will activate it in... on the pending later we will see different ways to
manage the feature flags and at the end you need to remove to retire the feature flag.
I told about the four types. Those are the timelines, the
expiration, the usual expiration for them.
Once you do a release, you need to do a new branch just to remove the feature
flag related to the release because it's working. You don't need a permanent
shield. If you need a permanent shield for a release you did a couple of weeks
ago, probably you don't trust in your code and you have another issues related
with that new code and you need to ask yourself why I don't trust in my code.
Experiment again is for a season to take some data when you finish that, remove it.
Operational, if you have a problem about your resources you need to regulate
schedule or to have a panic button to solve. Imagine, I don't know, let's use a
comparison. Imagine you have a highway to the direction.
Regularly you need to steal part of the one side and give that side to the other
direction because you have more cars in one direction and you need to steal more
resources. If you need it regularly for years you have a problem. You need to fix
that. Stop that patch, fix the problem you have in your system and remove the
operational feature flags. Well, probably the mission feature flags can live
eternally because it's a way to handle the how users use the system and well
the user level you don't modify dramatically the user levels in the
system normally. Disadvantages there but I prefer to try to tell you the good
one things and at the end I will tell you a lot of things that can be bad.
Why feature flags? Okay, for the rest, I like to rest at night. It's like they are a
shield, they reduce risk, we say that they are rollback, okay, it's a problem.
Okay, and do, sorry, and do the let's switch the feature flag of the last
release and do the changes. Well, not undo the changes logically and do the
changes. You are not modifying the code. We don't want that. The problem
antecedent. Okay, do you know the play I never? It's a drinking game. Every time I
never you drink, okay. I don't want you drink but just think about that. I never
work without preprode environment. Okay, probably that was a good moment to use
feature flags. I never release a project we have code for months or one year
at once at the end totally. Yeah, a lot of QA, a lot of unit test and to end test
but not real in production. I never deploy refactor a feature I don't trust
totally. I have done all of them don't worry.
Deploy without performance test, without test. Keep the old code and use a new one.
I remember my first position. I was down, but developer. Sorry. Yeah, now it's
hype. You are waiting for the... I had a complex query. I remember it was done
SQL, directly SQL or RM and it was very, very slow. I was able to do a better one
but sometimes the better one fails. So I had to try the better one, catch the bad
one. I mean the solution is to fix the thing but if you need to deploy that,
okay, use a feature flags. Try the good one and again try to fix that cheat code
you have developed. Probably you can imagine another hattie pattern action
you have done. Well, all those scenarios are good scenarios. You can improve, you
can feel better, you can do better work if you use feature flags. Okay, the first
approach, the setting file. In the intuition, when intuitively, sorry,
that's the intuition says when you don't know about feature flags is, okay, I need
to modify how my system works. So sometimes constant file, variable
file is created. It works. I need to test something in production so I create a
user or a company in production so we can simulate whether...
and you work for a while with that or you can, anytime you develop something new
you have the new feature variable and you pack your new code around and if my
new freighter do the new logic of the case, the old logic.
Talking again about the four-object if I set for myself at the beginning, this
solution doesn't solve the downtime. You need to deploy every time you want to
change anything. Unless you have another tool you are going to have some
downtime. You probably can monitor the changes because probably you will have
your monitoring tool and will work. It's not the couple. This logic
effect is inside, fully inside in the code. So you didn't decode the code and
you are limited to Python. You are doing the changes in Python. Okay, the
first improving or the first way that people improve this approach, when
people discover feature flags, it's people start to use some of those
libraries. I find, but limited to. For me the most important limit is sometimes
you are deploying a new feature and you want to double check the performance
issues. You want first day just 10% of the user use the new feature. Those
libraries and that's saying I said that. Well, where for it does. They have
another limit. The code, the logic, keep being into the code or in the
Django admin. I will show you. Everybody in the company has access to all the
features. So if you are in a big company, people, they don't understand totally.
They don't have the expertise of a part of the application can do
modification in some feature flags. Django catch, the different ways we have to, the
different catch we have can affect if you have a, if you are catching users, for
example, you have a feature flag that check the user, you can have problem
between the real because it was a recent update or between the behavior in your
local and in your remote because the distributed catch. Well, how it was
Django flash. Hello. You set a lot of a set of flags. Also, you put in the
template, you put the check and if the check is true, it shows that part of
the code. Also, admit a modification in URLs. If you have a get, you can put in
the parameter of the get feature flags and set the value through our files and
you will receive the information on the pending the true or false value. You can
manage it into your Django admin. You can define a lot.
Enticonditions, with condition, multiple conditions required, dictionaries. There
are some combinations that it allows but probably are not a good idea because if
you have a dictionary but also are required, take care. When you have complex
feature flags, maybe you will take a look in the logic and split the class or the
feature because, well, you know, keep it simple. Those are the pros. Yeah, you can
use flags. You can put a flag, sorry, you can use decorator. You can put a
feature flag as a decorator and all the code run will accept that value for the
flag, dearly, without asking. You can get all the features, status at once. We have
some improvements but the co-play, not yet. The only front thing we can use with
this is the Django template. Waffles is better because it's simple. Just one
fraction. Hello to customize the class. Hello groups. You say,
present as you use. It allowed to use Waffle. Yes. So it's wider, the scope of
where you can use that. It has simple feature flags, switch, just all or
nothing. Yeah, the summary. Guy Goyle, for me, is not much better than Django
Flash. Also, it's deprecated but, well, probably the best thing that it does is
testing. It's better for testing. It has a good system of decorator for testing.
We will see one of the good things or one of the good habits we should have
with feature flags is do test. Test when the feature flag is true and when it falls.
Guy Goyle does. Yeah, on the limits. Well, third parties. Those third parties I have
used, they are very, very, very complete. It's full of features. They allow
percentages, allow set of uses, allow a lot of parameters to define. They allow
things that some software consider anti-patterns. They put as feature. Oh, yeah.
Sorry. Amen. We are able to do this. No, that's a good thing. A bad thing. They have
multi-language. You can do with mobile, frontend, bucket languages, whatever. They
allow kill switch. We will talk later. They deploy multivariant, a lot of things.
Now, you will have the if with all. If feature flag. But you don't know in your code what
does that feature flag. The definition, all the behavior of the feature flag is on a
board out of your system. It's like calling an API and, hey, this variable, what means
this variable? They allow to have domains of variables. So imagine you are in a big
company. You are on charge of seeing new uses. That your team just is on charge of that.
You have the feature flags related to that. You don't know which feature flag has other
people. Nothing like that. And they don't know. And they can't modify your system without
your knowledge. They solve, they obey kill everything you need. You can take whatever
you want off of those if you want to do whatever. And what I should do? Buy a third party, sorry,
or build a library. Take a look at the prost on each and choose. For me, my advice is you
can take a library, but do an effort to pack it as much the logic as much as you can into
a pattern or a larger or whatever. So for the regular developer, they will feel they are
using a third party. That will allow you to migrate just in case you need a third party
with more functionalities and so on. Okay. Feature Flags versus Blue Green. Blue Green
is a way to deploy. Feature Flags is able to do more things than just deploying. Those
are the, for me, the most important difference is related with the environments. You need
less environment with Feature Flags, sorry, in case of a rollback. Blue Green is, you
need to return to the other environment. In Feature Flags, you just switch a bottom. Yeah,
from the Feature Flags perspective. This is configuration manager. Well, this is the
difference. Feature Flags should die. That means you need to do two things or you duplicate
the work. One is to create and the other one is to remove it. More you keep, more Feature
Flags you keep in your code. More combat your system into a net. Good principle of Feature
Flags. Some people try to use what people call the Feature Flags pattern. It's Feature
Flags tutorial. I tried to code it for Python, but I just found it in Java and I hadn't time
enough to bring that here. Good principle is great test. Both cases active on or off,
but great test for both cases. You need to ensure what happened in both cases. Keeping
it to mind, remove the flag. Keep a high level of communication. This is very important.
You should tell everybody in the company you know you are going to do something in the
logic. Something that can affect. I mean, I don't know. I don't know. I don't say everybody
in the company. Committee, responsibility person in each team, but communication should happen.
Hey, we are in payment and we are going to modify the default payment system or whatever,
so if people detect something happens, they can think, okay, this is because we have something
or this is because they had something one hour ago. Communication is needed. Nobody
want to become crazy in a big company because someone in other, anyone in any place, modify
something and say nothing. Deploy small features. Again, small pieces managed by Fitoo Flags.
Naming conversation for deploy, for operation Fitoo Flags, use it. Keep the logic simple.
Long chain Fitoo Flags and the hider is tried to be able to backwire always. We don't want
that. We don't want that. Really. And those are the last screens. The risk. There are
a lot of things. Well, I just showed you in the previous one what happened if you abuse
the lag communication, the lag compatibility. We have talked about most of them. What happened,
yeah, when you have a synchronous task and you change the logic or you change the logic
for 10% of the user and they stop calling some asynchronous task. What happened with
them? With some processes pending. Automatic test is hided to keep them working. Complexity
is increasing. There is a standard source of true. You have a board out of your system.
If you use a third party, you have a board. That was says when the Fitoo Flag is running
and that is not in your code. You have your hider open, your idea open. Also you have
your web browser in the other side. You need to keep checking. Confusions, people modifying.
Different behavior between preproduction, production, testing local and the catches.
Some basis people acquire or embrace with Fitoo Flags. It's okay. I have a Fitoo Flag
to rescue me. I can test in production. Release and monolithic release. Leaving the date,
imagine, I don't know, you have an API version one. You create the version two and you say,
10% of my user they are using version one. I'm going to keep the version one. No, I mean
two microservices but no Fitoo Flags, please. And force your user to move to the second
version, please. Tolerance to inefficient code. I told my experience many years ago
that this is a sheet but used to work and I have the rescue plan in the ELSE. Yeah, allow
bad deploy processes. Finishing, I swear. Other things I saw and I read, people sharing
code. I'm going to pass this code. I'm going to involve in a Fitoo Flag and I'm going
to tell to my college, hey, my working code, my web code is there but there is a Fitoo
Flag. Hey, don't worry, it's not going to be run. Related with testing production,
binding to production, something is not ready. Deploying everything at the end. The version
in things, the version in APIs, I told. And the kill switches. We know we can switch off
a Fitoo Flag in production but don't rely on that. Try to avoid it. It's like a panic
button and nobody wants to press panic button every day. That is part of the bibliography.
There is a lot of. Yeah, I work in Singular. They love to hire people. Please, I lost an
opportunity to put my social networks there because if you go there by me, I get money
but you can find me, please. Thanks a lot.