No, actually, it looks there's some issues.
Okay.
I think so.
So, again, sorry for the delay.
We are going to try to stay to schedule five minutes or less.
So, this is San Miguel.
Leiva is going to talk about 500,000 flow, so cool lines of testing topics.
And, yeah, I'm going to give him the floor.
Give him a big applause, please.
Okay.
Hello.
Thank you very much for coming.
I'm José Leiva.
I work for ETS, a financial advisory firm that applies quantitative methods to its products.
And they've been doing it for since the early 80s, which is quite remarkable, I think.
I know the title is very appealing, but I hope not all of you came here looking for
fast and easy money, but to learn new stuff and have some fun.
We are going to have fun because we are going to talk about very exciting topics.
Machine learning.
Everybody is talking about machine learning.
Deep learning.
Everybody is talking about deep learning.
Quantitative finance.
Many people are talking about quantitative finance as well.
So, let's start with machine learning.
There have been some talks in the Python about machine learning and workshops yesterday with
several definitions about machine learning.
I'll give you the right one.
So imagine you want to build automatic digital recognition.
Machine learning deals with learning from examples.
To simplify the problem, imagine we only have two kinds of digits.
We only have to distinguish the ones from the eights.
So the first step in our automatic system would be to transform that information into
numerical information.
So remember that a digital image is nothing but metrics of numbers.
So each pixel in the image is just a number.
I love that it illustrates very well what a digital image is.
So from now on, we have two alternatives.
We could try to solve this problem in the original representation space.
So there are almost 800 pixels in that image.
So we have almost 800 dimensions.
Or we could try to extract discriminative features from the images.
In this case, we could try to extract the eight and the width of the image.
There's been some issue changing the resolution of the screen, but this would be the height
of the letter.
This would be the width.
And we hope that the width, for example, is discriminative and will help us distinguish
between the ones and the eights.
So if I plot these two variables for our different examples, I would expect to be able to draw
a boundary between them to discriminate between the two classes.
So performing a linear classification boils down to performing the linear, the scalar
product between the vector that characterizes this hyperplane and each of the vectors.
Good.
So very often, we are interested in obtaining probabilistic estimation, or in other words,
degree of the confidence about our prediction.
For example, answers of the kind, I'm 80% sure that this is a one.
What we need now is numerical transformation between the previous scalar product into a
number between zero and one.
So we can use the sigmoid.
The sigmoid, you can forget about the equation if you don't feel comfortable with the equation
and focus on the shape of the sigmoid.
It maps any number between minus infinite to plus infinite into a number between zero
and one.
Great.
The fundamental problem in machine learning is to obtain the optimal separating hyperplane
or the optimal boundary between the classes.
So the way to do that consists of measuring the cost of the error and minimize that measurement.
So a first approach would be just to count the errors.
Counting the errors.
So many errors means a bad separating hyperplane.
Few errors means a good separating hyperplane.
Would that be a good idea to try to optimize that number?
It looks like a good idea.
But if you think carefully, if you move the boundary a little bit, nothing happens, but
then you move it a little bit more and some of the samples jump to the other side.
So the function is stepwise and numerical methods for optimization don't like that kind
of functions.
They like smooth functions so that they can find their way to the lowest value possible.
So another alternative, which is the one we are going to focus on, is the log loss, also
called the entropy loss, which is the one usually employed in neural networks.
There are other alternatives.
I'd like to show you the maximum margin criterion, which is very easy to understand.
The maximum margin criterion tells you that you should put the hyperplane so that the
margin to the closest samples is as large as possible.
But as I told you, we are going to use the log loss.
The log loss is like this.
Again, I wouldn't like to focus too much on the equations.
But if you think about this, if you predict correctly a given example, this is a number
close to one and the logarithm of one is zero.
So that cost is zero.
No error means no cost.
But if you are predicting a low probability for a correct example or a correct class,
in that case, you have a positive cost, which means that that error is costing you something.
Great.
So how can we perform machine learning with Python?
Psychic learn is the best way to approach machine learning in Python.
So I guess many of you already know it.
Psychic learn has a lot of positive features.
One of them is object oriented, so it's very comfortable to work with.
So I'll give you a couple of snippets.
The classifier that we have seen before is called the logistic regression.
The logistic regression uses a reasonable loss function.
It has a magical property because when the log loss that we have mentioned is combined
with the sigmoid, so it's the superposition of two functions, and that superposition is
a convex function.
So convex functions are easy to optimize because they have a unique lowest point.
You can think of them as a bowl.
A bowl has a unique lowest point, so the numerical algorithm just looks for the steepest direction
downwards.
So if we want to apply a logistic regression, we just import the logistic regression from
SK Learn.
We create a model.
We feed the model to some training examples, and then we can apply the model to new examples,
either to obtain the class, 0 or 1, or 1 versus 8, or to predict the probability, the probability
estimated for the prediction.
And if you want to evaluate the accuracy of the prediction, we can import also the accuracy
score, but anyway, the score is also a method of the model, so you can use it to obtain
the accuracy of your prediction.
So of course machine learning is far more than this, but I have tried to give you some
of the main points.
The importance of feature extraction, the importance of probability estimation, and
the need of an appropriate loss function, something that penalizes the errors in a reasonable
way, and at the same time is smooth and convex.
So now we are ready to jump from machine learning to deep learning.
You can think of deep learning in terms of the simple classifier that we have seen, the
logistic regressor.
Imagine that you use it as the building block of something bigger.
Imagine that instead of just taking the output of the logistic regression as your prediction,
you use it as the input of several other logistic regressions in another layer, and those outputs
at the same time are applied to a new layer and so on.
And it can be, if you do it with many layers, that's called deep learning.
This particular kind of networks, this particular kind are called fully connected networks,
or dense networks.
The good thing about this is that each of those units has a nonlinear activation function.
If you think of the sigmoid, each of those units has a sigmoid at the output.
So that nonlinear transformation makes these kind of models far more powerful because now
we can draw nonlinear separating boundaries between the classes.
So that's the nice thing about this.
And you can also think about the analogy with a biological neuron.
A biological neuron receives inputs from many other neurons, typically thousands of other
neurons, and it activates only when the incoming signals are above a certain threshold.
So that's a nonlinear behavior.
It's a binary behavior.
I told you about the sigmoid, but the activation function, that nonlinear activation function
that is much popular in the state of the art models, is the rectified linear unit which
has this shape.
So that's the one usually employed in deep architecture.
In fully connected models, we have other architecture, for example, the convolutional neural networks.
The CNNs are used in image classification with great success, and it's based on performing
a different kind of arithmetic based on convolutions.
You can think of a convolution as a set of filters that increase the depth of the image.
The original depth of the image is given by the number of colors, and as you go deep into
the network, the size of the image is lower, but the depth is higher.
And it is on those pseudo colors where we are capturing the discriminative information.
And the neuroscientists know that this corresponds, this imitates very well how the neurons are
organized in the visual cortex.
There are neurons that are specialized in the first layers.
They are specialized in detecting low level patterns, such as horizontal lines, vertical
lines and so on.
And the neurons in the last layers, in the more advanced layers, are able to capture
higher level information, like recognizing the face of our friends and so on.
Apart from convolutional neural networks, we also have the recurrent neural network,
which is a conversional neural network with a feedback mechanism.
So when you try to represent the neural network a long time, the output for a given input
at a given instant depends on that input, but also on the previous history.
So that's why recurrent neural networks are so powerful when working with sequences in
applications such as machine translation or speech recognition.
The truth is that some of those architectures are often combined.
For example, a typical image recognition system uses several layers of convolutions and then
a fully connected layer in the end, because it is the fully connected architecture which
is able to draw that discriminative function, those flexible discriminative functions.
And when we try to recognize different classes, more than two classes, we need to generalize
the concept of sigmoid that we had before.
So we had something called the softmax function.
We have this equation, again, forget the equation, just consider that this transformation
makes that all the outputs, all the values at the output up to one.
So if we are trying to recognize between 10, 100 and digits, so the probability that we
assign to each of them must be equal, the summation of those values must be equal to
one.
So how can we perform deep learning with TensorFlow, deep learning with Python?
Well we can use several frameworks.
One of them is TensorFlow.
Yesterday there was an interesting workshop on TensorFlow.
In TensorFlow, it has many positive features, one of them is that it allows you to define
a graph of operations, but that step is separated to the step of executing those operations.
So if we want to perform something as simple as this equation, we first define the graph
with two variables and the result of the computation, and then we perform the execution
by creating a session, initializing the variables, and then running the computation.
And it can be done more compactly with this syntax.
The logistic regression that we have seen before can be defined very easily with those
steps.
We use a placeholder which is like the recipient that we create to put the training examples.
So we iterate and we are putting different examples on those placeholders.
Here we apply the softmax function and we evaluate the cost with the cross entropy loss
function.
So we have some snippet here for the execution and the optimization of the model, which is
the important thing about this.
To be able to optimize the variables of the model so that best fit into our training data.
So that's all it takes to do some machine learning or to work with neural networks in
Python with TensorFlow.
Can we apply these kind of models to financial problems?
Well, that's the next section of the talk.
In asset management or in portfolio management, we are interested or the problem is defined
as to distribute our wealth in several assets, our disposal.
There are several assets we can invest on them.
And we have to decide the fraction, the question should be in another place.
We have to obtain the weight which are the fraction of the wealth that we put in each
of the assets.
Those weights must adapt to one, obviously.
We consider the case in which all of them are positive and all of them are lower than
one, which means that you don't borrow more money for your investment.
Okay?
It's not working.
I'm having an issue.
I'm sorry I'm having an issue.
I'll try to anticipate the content just in case we are not able to load this.
I don't know what's going on.
Okay I think I have to do it with the role.
I don't know.
The presentation mode doesn't work.
Okay?
Okay.
Okay, okay.
So, in order to apply this kind of architecture to the problem of asset management, we can
use a conventional architecture because a multi-classification neural network gives you
a set of numbers that add up to one, but we must modify the cost function because now
what we would like to maximize is the profit of our investment of our strategy.
So this will be the TensorFlow model we use.
I cannot stop as long as I would like here,
because all the time is used.
So I'll skip to the results.
We are going to perform some experiments
in which we train a different neural network each year,
using data from the six previous years.
And we are going to use this portfolio.
We have five assets in our portfolio.
Four of them are equities, and one of them is just cash.
You might wonder why the price of the cash is not constant.
It's because of the interest rates.
We use daily price movements and weekly price movements
as the inputs of the network.
And these are our results.
The neural network performs reasonably well.
We compare it with some benchmarks.
One of the benchmarks is a portfolio
with equal weights for all of the assets.
And another benchmark would be a global index,
because our portfolio is made of global assets
from all over the world.
And we can also analyze the composition of our portfolio
a long time.
The different colors show you the proportion
at each instant during that period of three years and a half.
I'd like to point out a couple of things here.
One of them is that this strategy is too aggressive.
It wouldn't be accepted by most managers.
Actually, my colleagues from ETS here
must be flipping out to see this graph.
And there are another interesting issue,
which is that we only have cash in 2014.
I said before that we are training the network
with the six last years.
That means that for 2014, we are training since 2008.
There was a crash in 2008.
So the network, in that case, has learned what a crash is.
So that's why the network has learned that keeping some cash
could be a good idea as a safety board.
But for the following years, the network
has been trained only with bullish markets, which
means that the prices have been consistently going up.
And that's the reason why it considers that cash doesn't work.
OK, so I'd like to finish with a reflection.
There's a controversial question about whether it's
possible to consistently beat the market.
I found a brilliant sentence by Nate Silver in this book,
The Signal and the Noise.
Highly recommended.
It's a delicious reading.
I'll make no comments about that.
But I think it describes very well how difficult this is.
And that would be all.
I'll give you our coordinates in social media.
And I strongly recommend you to take a look to our blog
with interesting discussions about Python, machine learning,
asset management, and so on.
So thank you.
Thank you.
So sadly, we don't have time for Kirsten.
Sorry, but maybe you can find these bigger files.
Thank you very much.
OK, thank you.
I thought it would be more flexible with time,
because of the technical details.
But I've given you five minutes more.
If we don't have all the time,
because we're going to have to do it again,
but I haven't given you the time to do anything.
I've given you the time you don't know.